ʻʻ'ʰʰʸ ʰʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸ.
ʻʻʻ'ʰʰʸ ʰʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸʸ.
ʰʰʰʸʸ.
ʰʰʰʸʸ.
Remind you that this speech is in progress, please wear a mask throughout
提醒您本演讲进行中 敬请全程配戴口罩
And eating and drinking video and audio recording are prohibited
并禁止饮食 录影及录音
Do not use the flash when taking pictures
拍照时请勿使用闪光灯
Thank you for your cooperation
感谢您的配合
In addition, in order to make our activities better, we need your valuable opinions
另外为了使我们的活动更好 需要您的宝贵意见
Please help us scan the QR code of the reward provider before leaving the venue
离场前请帮我们扫描奖励商的QR Code
Fill out the online questionnaire
填达线上问卷
After confirming the completed screen to the service desk staff outside the city
将完成画面给城外服务台工作人员确认后
Thanks
谢谢
A nice little courtesy thank you
的精美小禮儀份 謝謝
Academia Sinica's 110-year Knowledge Trial
中央研究院110年知識想驗
Dean Wang Shijie's popular science lecture begins
王世傑院長科普講座開始
Please invite Director Zeng Guoxiang of the Secretariat to host for us
有請秘書處曾國祥處長為我們主持
Family members of Academician Wang, Director Lei's speaker today
雷所長今天的主講人王院士的家屬
All advanced students present
在場的各位先進各位同學
Good night everyone online
以及線上的各位朋友大家晚安
I am Zeng Guoxiang, Director of the Secretariat of the Chinese Academy
我是中文院秘書處處長曾國祥
The secretariat is also a series of knowledge experiments
秘書處也是這一系列的知識想驗
The organizer of this lecture by Dean Gu
這個顧院長講座的主辦單位
Originally this lecture should be given by us
本來這個講座應該是由我們
Vice President Wang personally hosted but because
王副院長親自主持但因為
In fact, something happened, so please let me host it instead of him.
其實有事所以請我代替他主持
Then there is a huge difference between my academic second and the associate dean.
那我的學術第二跟副院長那是這個天差地別
It's just that everyone is here today, the important thing is not the host
索性大家今天來這裡其實重要的不是主持人
The most important thing today is of course our keynote speaker
今天最重要的當然是我們的主講人
I believe that everyone is also here to admire the name.
那相信大家也都是慕名而來
Because the Director of Lei, Mr. Lei Xiangning
因為這個雷所長雷翔寧老師
He is a very famous and outstanding historian in Taiwan
他是台灣非常出名傑出的一位歷史學家
In fact, he graduated from the Chemistry Department of National Taiwan University.
他事實上是台大化學系畢業
PhD in History of Science from the University of Chicago
之後在芝加哥大學取得科學史的博士學位
So this is crossing a big boundary
所以這個是跨了一個很大的界
Then his research works are very many, very profound.
那他的研究著作非常的多非常的深刻
Moreover, his most important works are published by famous foreign university presses.
而且他最重要的著作都是由國外著名的大學出版社所出版
including his alma mater's prestigious University of Chicago Press
包括他的母校著名的芝加哥大學出版社
So today I have the opportunity to give you the opportunity to
所以今天能夠有機會在這個場合大家
Gathering together, Mr. Lin Ting's speech I believe is a guarantee for everyone
齊聚一堂林廷老師的演講我相信是一個保證大家
Very enjoyable evening myself and a lover of reading
非常愉快的夜晚我自己也是一個喜歡閱讀
A man of history is not an expert in history
歷史的人雖然不是一個歷史學的專家
Well, what we're going to talk about today is actually very interesting.
那我們今天要講的題目其實是很有趣的
Because today, of course, in the past two or three years, everyone knows
因為今天當然這兩三年大家知道
Our lives have been greatly affected by the epidemic
我們的生活受到疫情很大的影響
But in fact, the epidemic has changed human society
可是事實上這個疫病對人類社會的改變
Of course he didn't die today, everyone probably knows that.
當然不是死於今天這大概都知道
In fact, for example, in the 1930s there was a very famous
事實上舉例而言在1930年代就有一個非常著名的
This so-called Chinese tuberculosis is a mystery
這個所謂的中國肺結核的一個謎吧
Because in fact at the time
因為事實上在當時在當年
China is not the most industrialized country
中國並不是一個最工業化的國家
But the death rate of people in China who suffer from tuberculosis
可是中國的人得肺結核的死亡率
four times that of a country like the UK
卻是像英國這種國家的四倍
That sometimes seems like such a mystery
那有時候就好像這樣一個謎團
Maybe our on-site factory store is interesting, it's a biomedical institute
也許我們現場廠店很有趣是生醫所
This may not be the person who actually made the vaccine
這就可能不是真的是做疫苗的人
Questions that can be answered by people who actually do medical treatment
做實際去做醫療的人所能夠去解答的問題
This is through history
這就要透過歷史
Through historians' re-combating in the beginning
透過歷史學家在始料的重新的爬梳
Come and tell us to solve this very interesting mystery
來告訴我們解開這個非常有趣的謎團
and then through this question
然後從而透過這個問題
can make us reflect
能夠讓我們反省
Today, we are also living with this era of vaccines.
在今天我們一樣是在跟這個疫苗共處的時代裡面
How do we get from vaccines
我們如何從疫苗
Then reflect on ourselves from this disease
然後從這個疾病來反省我們自己
Relationships with people, society, and society
跟人跟社會跟社會所有的關係
And then go on to allow ourselves to understand the history of infectious diseases on our bodies
然後進而讓我們自己對傳染病對我們的身體史
have a richer understanding
能夠有一個比較豐富的認識
And then to our own times
進而對我們自己所處的時代
Especially civilized, East Asian, these issues of modernity
特別文明 東亞 現在性這些問題
have a chance to reflect
都能夠有一個反省機會
then today we will
那今天我們就
Wait a minute and I can invite this teacher to give a speech
等一下馬上就可以把這個請的老師來演講
In the end, everyone can probably tell from the beginning.
那最後大概就是大家從頭聽會看得出來
Also, he was talking about a vaccine
一樣他講的是一個好像跟疫苗
no immediate relationship
沒有馬上直接的關係
i think we have dinner today
我覺得我們今天吃飯
This Chinese dining table has a rotating table
這個中式餐桌都有一個旋轉的那個旋轉台
His birth through this revolving table
他透過這個旋轉台的誕生
What I want to tell us is exactly the mystery I left just now.
要替我們說的剛好就是我剛才所留下的那個迷
It is China's understanding and fame
就是中國的被解和知名
As for the detailed reasons
至於詳細的原因是什麼
Shall we give Mr. Lei a big round of applause?
我們是不是就熱烈掌聲歡迎雷老師
come and speak for us
來替我們講演
thank you thank you everyone
謝謝 謝謝大家
my mic is on
我的麦克风是打开的
open?
开了吗?
both are open
两个都开了
The back seems to be open
后面就好像都开了
That's good
那就好
good
好
Thank you very much for the introduction of Yimei, the head of Pearl
非常谢谢珍珠长的意美的介绍
very honored
非常的荣幸
then i feel very honored
然后我觉得非常的荣幸
I had the opportunity to do this with you here today
今天有机会跟大家在这里做这个
Lecture by Dean Wang Shijie of Academia Sinica
中研院王世杰院长的科幅讲座
Especially this relative of President Wang is here
特别是王院长的这个亲人在这边
Because it was actually last year that I had the chance
因为其实也是去年我才有机会
Until that is to say, the European and American office opposite the technical office
直到就是说在技职所对面的那个欧美所
that beautiful building
那个很漂亮的建筑
It was designed by Ms. Wang Qinghua, the daughter of President Wang.
就是王院长的女儿王清华女士所设计的
just know a lot of his stories
就才知道很多他的故事
So it's a double honor
所以特别感到双重的荣幸
I am very glad to have the opportunity to do this report with you.
很高興能有機會跟大家做這個報告
So hello friends here and friends online
那個 所以在座的朋友和線上的朋友大家好
That's the topic I want to talk about today
那個 我今天想講這個題目
I want to say that when you see it, you don’t know how it feels
我在想說 大家看到的時候不知道有什麼感覺
should come to mind right away
應該會立刻就想到
What is a Chinese revolving table
中式旋轉餐台是什麼東西
mask good thanks
口罩 好 謝謝
Thanks
謝謝
That is, let me start with our topic and introduce to you
就是 我就先從我們的題目開始跟大家介紹
The main axis that I will talk about today
我今天要講的主軸
First of all, we are all so familiar that it may be difficult for us to imagine
首先 我們都太熟悉了 所以我們可能很難想像
Foreigners in this picture will be very surprised to find
在這張照片裡面的外國人會非常吃驚的發現
There's something on this table they've never seen
這個桌上有他們從來都沒有看過的
a piece of furniture
一個家具
It's the revolving table we just talked about
就是我們剛剛講這個旋轉餐台
Then this is a very familiar thing to us
那這個對我們來講是一個非常熟悉的東西
So I think it might be hard for you to imagine saying
所以我想大家可能很難以想像說
In fact, before the 20th century, on the Chinese dining table
其實在20世紀之前中式餐桌上
Such a convenient piece of furniture does not exist
這麼方便的一個家具是不存在的
This is actually a new invention to the 20th century
這是居然是個新發明到20世紀
right
對不對
and then the second
然後第二呢
Japan and Korea who also use chopsticks
同樣用筷子的日本跟韓國
We can't see the carousel either
我們也看不到這個旋轉餐台
Unless you go to his Chinese restaurant
除非你到他的那個中餐廳裡去
In fact, the Japanese think
那事實上日本人認為
This is what they invented
這個是他們發明的
that's a
那這是一個
Be independent of me for stories other than today's story
跟我獨立我今天故事之外的故事
If you are interested, I will talk to you later
大家有興趣我待會再跟大家講
that's the second place
那這是第二個地方
may surprise everyone
可能會讓大家感到意外
The third point is
第三點呢就是
It's not just a simple piece of furniture
它其實不是一個簡單的家具而已
when it was invented
它被發明的時候
is closely related to public health
是跟公共衛生有密切的關係
even has an english name
甚至有個英文名字
It's called Hygienic Chinese Dining Table
叫做Hygienic Chinese Dining Table
A Chinese sanitary dining table
一個中式衛生餐台
So it has something to do with our current epidemic situation.
所以跟我們今天的疫情是有關係的
And what?
而且呢
Its inventor was in fact
它的發明人事實上是
Many people know today
今天很多人都知道的
Dr. Wu Liande
就是五連德博士
He is the Chinese
他是那個華裔的
Citizens in British Malaya
在英屬馬來亞的公民
A Doctor of Medicine from Jianqiao University
建橋大學的一個醫學博士
is that
是算是那個
And it's important
而且很重要一點呢
He is recognized for his research
他以屬於的研究而容獲
In 1935, he received the Liu Beier medical certificate
1935年容獲劉貝爾醫學
nomination for a scholarship
一學獎提名
So should be the first to be nominated
所以應該是第一個被提名
A person of Chinese descent who won the Nobel Prize in Medicine
諾貝爾一學獎的一個華裔人士
now about him
那現在關於他
he's become very very famous now
他現在變得非常非常有名
partly because
有一個部分的原因是
After the discovery of the COVID outbreak
在COVID疫情發現之後呢
everyone thinks
大家認為
The inventor of the anti-epidemic mask we wear today
我們今天帶的這個防疫口罩的發明人
maybe it's him
可能就是他
In fact, most of our inventions have previous
那其實我們大部分的發明都有前面的
previous story
前面的故事
It's hard to say who invented
也很難說誰發明
But now if you go to Google
但是現在就是大家如果去Google一下
Go check CAN
去查CAN啊
some mainstream media
一些主流媒體
will say
都會說
This is the time when the Manchurian plague was fought five years ago
這是五年得戰滿洲鼠疫的時候
From 1910 to 1911
1910到1911的時候
invented this
發明的這個
It is the first pioneer in the use of anti-epidemic masks by humans
是人類最早開始使用防疫口罩的先驅
So he's now become this international celebrity
所以他現在變成一個這個國際知名人士
When I first started researching him
我一開始研究他的時候
In fact, it was the situation when SARS was over.
其實是SARS完的時候的情況
that is such a person
那是這樣的一個人
so think about it
所以大家想想看
It's actually an interesting story
這其實是個很有趣的故事
One we use everyday at home
一個我們家裡日常使用
we even thought
我們甚至以為
It may have been used for hundreds of thousands of years
是可能用了幾百年幾千年
very convenient piece of furniture
很方便的一個家具
It actually had to wait until the 20th century for it to be invented
居然要等到二十世紀才被發明
and still a
而且還是一個
Invented by Nobel-Lectured Scientists
諾貝爾講級的科學家發明的
Think about it, if we now know
大家想想看如果我們現在知道
that our current dean
那個我們現在的院長
Or the former vice president of Jianren
或者說是前建人副院長
He actually designed it for us
他居然幫我們設計了
an item on our dinner table at home
我們家裡餐桌上的一個東西
Everyone must be surprised, right?
大家一定都會很吃驚對不對
So inside this shadow
所以這個影子裡面
In fact, it implies that
其實隱含就是說
During our epidemic prevention process
在我們的防疫的過程中
In fact, some of them are very deep
其實有一些是非常深入的
into our daily life
進入我們的日常生活之中
and then become our
而且然後成為我們的
part of life
生活裡的一個部分
so my today
那所以我今天的
at that time
當時呢
When Wuliande designed
五連德設計的時候
is to solve a
是要解決一個
The most important cause of death in China at that time
當時中國最重要的死因
It's what Director Zeng mentioned just now.
就是剛剛那個曾處長提到的
It's Fei Jie and
就是費傑和
so there's a very serious reason
所以是一個非常嚴肅的原因
and this
而且這個
This photo and this article
這個照片跟這個文章
on board
就登在
The National Medical Journal of China 的
The National Medical Journal of China 的
The first issue of the first issue in 1915
創刊號1915年的第一期
As far as today's so-called Chinese Medical Journal
就今天所謂的中華醫學雜誌
So you read an English medical journal
所以你看一個英文醫學雜誌
The first issue of the inaugural issue published a photo
創刊的第一期登出一個照片
Then to address the most important cause of death
然後要解決一個最重要的死因
But there is indeed one that none of us know today
但是確實一個我們今天大家都不知道
Furniture Invented in Taipei in the Second Century
二世紀台北發明的家具
So this is what I want to tell you today
那所以這是我今天想跟大家
So I want to share with you through this story
所以我想要透過這個故事來跟大家分享
some bigger questions
一些更大的問題
So if the simplest speech
所以如果最簡單的講話
China is a very simple story
中華是一個很簡單的故事
That is why the prevention and control of infectious diseases will promote
就是傳染病的防治為什麼會促使
Nobel-Lecture Physician
諾貝爾講級的醫學家
Design a brand new daily necessities?
設計出一個嶄新的日常生活的用品呢
like i just said
就像我剛剛講的
if we want now
如果我們現在想
that our dean
那個我們的院長
Help us design supplies for our home
幫我們設計給我們家裡的用品
Everyone should be surprised, right?
大家應該會很吃驚對不對
But I'm in the process of solving this mystery
可是我在解開這個謎的過程中
Actually what I want to say is
其實我想要說的就是說
we prevent the epidemic
我們防疫
In fact, everyone should feel
其實大家應該都會感覺到
How much our lives have changed in the past two years
過去兩年我們的生活改變能多大
after two years
經過這兩年之後
The whole world is different, right?
整個世界都不一樣對不對
But the story I want to tell today is
可是我今天想講的故事是
In addition to the many changes we know
除了我們知道的很多改變以外
and some more
還有一些更
deep change
深入的改變
we may not realize so easily
我們可能沒有那麼容易意識到
There is a series of changes initiated
有一系列的改變被啟動
The anti-epidemic measures developed to combat infectious diseases
那為了對抗傳染病而發展出來的防疫措施
How has prompted a series of new developments
如何促使了一系列的新發展
We may not often think of
我們平常可能不常想到
Contains the new living appliances of our life
包含有我們生活新的生活器具
Awareness and feelings of a new body
新的一個身體的意識和感受
change in your body
就你的身體改變
The sense of body has also changed
身體感也改變了
and your habit change
還有你的習慣改變
Sanitation habits have changed
衛生習慣改變了
The habit of speaking English is your second nature
英文說習慣就是你的second nature
right
對不對
You have changed in a profound sense
就很深遠的意義上你改變了
Even the relevant ethical values ​​have changed
甚至於相關的倫理價值也改變了
and my generals and
還有我的將界和
Relationships and general boundaries have also changed
關係和將界也改變了
That's my topic at the end
那最後就是我的題目
Finally
最後講到
Individual and group self-identities are also altered
個人和群體的自我認同也發生了改變
so i think
所以我想
I often pass this one
我常常通過這一個
A specific story about the Chinese rotating ginseng pan
中式旋轉參盤這個具體的一個故事
Then we see every day may not know
然後我們每天都看到可能不知道
we have a history of this history
我們有一個歷史的這個歷史
to make everyone feel
來讓大家感覺到說
We are in the process of epidemic prevention
我們在防疫的一個過程中
What profound changes have been caused
引發了多麼深層的改變
There are so many facets
有這麼多的面向
And what?
而且呢
These aspects are often not legal
這些面向很多時候不是以法條
not by thought
不是以思想
but in an instrumental or bodily way
而是以一種器具或者肉體的方法
changed us
改變了我們
become a part of us
成為我們的一個部分
In the end it means
那最後就是說
If everyone thinks you're surprised too
如果大家也覺得你很吃驚
This thing is actually a
這個東西居然是一個
If medical experts found out on a Japanese TV station
醫學專家在日系一台發現的話
It provides a very important clue that
它就提供一個很重要的線索就是說
It is because we all think of epidemic prevention as
就是因為我們都把防疫想成
just to prevent contagion
只是防止傳染病
and just help us to be healthy
和只是幫助我們健康
we think of it as a tool
我們把它想成一個工具
So we didn't realize the change
所以我們沒有意識到這個改變
is a comprehensive cultural change
是一個全面性的一個文化的改變
And implement it in our body
而且落實在我們身體上
so we often
所以我們常常
didn't realize the change
沒有知覺到這個改變的
changing presence
改變的存在
That's a hidden history
那這是一個 hidden 的一個歷史
That's one I want to share with you today
那這是我今天想跟大家分享的一個
one
一個
behind a big background
背後的一個大的背景
Of course one of them
那當然其中一個
I hope we
希望我們
That is to say, when everyone listens to such a story
就是說大家聽完這樣的故事的時候
also feel that
也會感覺到說
Some epidemic prevention measures we usually think about
我們平常想的一些防疫的措施
In fact, the impact on us
其實對我們造成的影響
maybe more than we thought
也許比我們想的
There are many far-reaching
還有深遠的非常多
that's the one behind me
那這是我背後的一個
big idea
大的一個想法
OK, so let's start talking about this now.
好 那我們現在就開始來講這個
Why is his tuberculosis problem
為什麼他肺結核的問題
He will think about this place
他會往這個地方想過去
This is a Japanese book
這是一個那個日本的書喔
First published in 1914 as Tuberculosis and Digestion
初版於1914年叫肺結核與消化
Diagram of the spreading system of fine infectious diseases
細性傳染病蔓延系統圖
Then he talks about bubble contagion
然後他講泡沫傳染
That should be what we call today
那應該就是我們今天稱之為
Droplet infection, right?
飛沫傳染對不對
Then here we see a person
那這邊就是我們看到一個人
Then this person is actually a
然後這個人其實就是一個
tuberculosis patients
肺結核的患者
He already consciously wants to cover his mouth with his hand
他已經有意識要用手遮口了
but this drool
但是這個口水
Then this picture may not be clear enough.
那這個圖可能還不夠清楚
They are actually red dots
其實都是紅點
start cumming on this guy
就開始射到這個人的身上
So what am I talking about now?
那其實這我現在講的是什麼呢
this is the nineteenth century
就是這就是十九世紀
very brilliant one
非常光輝燦爛的一個
low blood breakthrough
低血的突破
to the bacteria
就是到細菌
The discovery of germ theory
細菌學說的發現
Then I get from this
然後我從這個
We're all too familiar with this now
現在我們大家太熟悉這個
So it may be difficult for everyone to imagine the feeling
所以大家可能很難想像那個感
The sense of breakthrough
當時的突破感
just suddenly you feel
就突然之間你覺得
where you can't see
你看不到的地方
full of things that can make you sick
充滿了可以讓你生病的
sick germs, right?
生病的細菌對不對
then the danger is everywhere
然後危險無所不在
This is a
這是一個
Such a huge change in worldview
這樣一個巨大的一個世界觀的改變
so all of a sudden
那所以突然之間
Experts all over the world are busy doing it
全世界的專家都在忙著做這件事
Tell the public with various images
以各種的圖像來告訴民眾
In fact, there are all kinds of dangers around you.
其實你身邊充滿了各式各樣的危險
It's sprayed out here where you can't see it
你看不到的地方這邊噴出來的
All that comes out are red dots
噴出來的都是紅點
brings countless dangers
帶來了無數的危險
then you should feel a sense of dread
那你應該感覺到一種恐懼感
Then look at this cup over here
那另外你看這邊這個杯子上
It's also a red dot, right?
也是紅點對不對
so after this
所以從這之後
when you use someone else's cup
你在用別人的杯子的時候
It's completely different from before
跟之前就完全不一樣了
You'll feel like you're full of this germ
你會覺得到處都充滿了這個病菌
There are a lot of pictures showing you where it will happen
有非常多的圖告訴你在什麼地方會發生
For example, before people would
譬如說之前人們會
That's not the one that flips the book, right?
那個用手翻書不是那個對不對
Now you also think it might be a germ
現在你也覺得這樣可能會傳染病菌了
even like us or that
甚至像我們或者說那個
It turns out that grandparents chewed up food and gave it to children
本來祖父母就是把食物咬爛了給小孩吃
Now you think it's spreading germs too
現在你覺得也會傳播病菌
Even men's beards were shaved later
甚至於後來男人的鬍子也被剃掉了
Because I think your beard is easy to hide germs
因為覺得你的鬍子裡很容易藏病菌
And the equipment in our home has changed too.
還有我們家庭裡的設備也都改變了
In the past, there were a lot of designs that were easy to accumulate dust, right?
就是以前有非常多的設計都很容易積灰塵對不對
Now you think there's germs hiding there
現在你覺得那地方都會藏細菌
So in fact, learning from the novelty of this germ theory
所以其實從半學這個細菌學說的新奇
It's just that people's lives have changed a lot
就是人們的生活就發生很大的改變
And one very important point
而且一個很重要的一點呢
Is actually the concept of bacterial infection itself
是其實這個細菌傳染的概念本身
is a major breakthrough in human thought
是人類思想的一個重大的突破
Because of course it wasn't until the nineteenth century that we had infectious diseases
因為當然並不是到十九世紀我們才有傳染病
We've all heard of the Black Death, haven't we?
我們大家都聽過黑死病對不對
So then the Black Death is said to have killed one-third of Europe's population at that time
所以然後黑死病據說那時候奪走歐洲三分之一的人口
So people have known for a long time that there will be some diseases
所以人們老早就知道會有一些病
when it suddenly became popular
突然間流行起來的時候
Many people experience the same symptoms
很多人都出現相同的症狀
mass death
大量的人死亡
but the point is
可是重點是呢
before the breakthrough of germ theory
在細菌學說的突破之前
We think of people of this magnitude
我們想到這種大規模的人
died of the same disease
得同樣的病死亡的時候
This spotlight phenomenon
這個聚光的現象
people will think that it must be
人們會覺得說一定是
The power of concentrating light causes the phenomenon of concentrating light
聚光的力量造成聚光的現象
So what is the power of focus?
那什麼叫聚光的力量呢
for example
就譬如說
if say yes
如果說是
brand new tree
嶄新樹上來講
it could be cosmic influence
就可能是宇宙的影響
Of course the place speaks
那地方當然是會講說
climate change
氣候的變化
Or let's talk about burial devices, right?
或者我們講葬器對不對
As a result of the environment where there is a burial vessel in this place
就這個地方有一個葬器的環境的造成
or say you say yes
或者說你講說是
Like we talk about warming the mind, right?
像我們講溫神對不對
is the power of gods and ghosts
是神鬼的力量
just forget to imagine such a
就無論如何遺忘想像這樣一個
When a large-scale epidemic spreads rapidly
迅速流行的大型疫病的時候
you will think so
你都會覺得是
Must be the power of light
一定是聚光的力量
cause spotlight
造成聚光的現象
But after the germ theory happened,
可是細菌學說發生之後
we just started
我們才開始
able to imagine
能夠想像
It's not happening with spotlight power
這不是聚光力量發生的
this is one
這就是一個
one person to one person one person to one person
一個人傳給一個人一個人傳給一個人
spread rapidly
迅速傳播開的
You couldn't imagine before
之前你根本沒辦法想像
The power of one person is passed on one by one
這樣一個一個傳一個人的力量
Can suddenly spread to many people
能夠突然間散到很多人的身上
So what I want to say is
所以我想講的是說
the discovery of animalism itself
畜竟學說的發現本身
It also constitutes a breakthrough point in our human thinking
也構成我們人類思考的一個突破點
Feeling passed from person to person
覺得從唯一關的人傳人
Then it is possible to become a co-optic phenomenon
然後變成一個俱觀的現象是可能的
What is the simplest example of this
這最簡單的例子是什麼
One of the most familiar
現在大家最熟悉的一個
This method of spreading is actually computer poisoning
這樣的而傳播的方法其實就是電腦中毒
right
對不對
When one is poisoned, you can also be poisoned by millions
一中毒的時候你也可以幾百萬個都中毒
How would you describe it when it was poisoned?
那中毒的時候大家怎麼形容它
It's about viral infection, right?
就病毒傳染對不對
So the other way around is to say
所以反過來講就是說
This breakthrough model of viral and bacterial infection
病毒跟細菌傳染的這個突破性的模式
becomes a model for our understanding of an other infection
變成我們理解一個別的傳染的時候的一個模型
Because before that people can't imagine
因為在那之前人們沒辦法想像
contagion like this is possible
像這樣的傳染是可能的
So what I'm telling you now is that
所以我現在跟大家有點在講的是說
This whole breakthrough has to do with germ theory
這個整個的突破是跟細菌學說有關
it represents a new
它代表了一個新的
one thinking about things
一個想事情
A whole new way of thinking about things
全新的想事情的方式
that also has elements we are familiar with
那也有我們熟悉的元素
talk like here
像這邊就講說
you want to talk to this patient
你要跟這個病人
To maintain a relationship of more than three feet
要維持三尺以上的關係
or you will be infected
不然你會被傳染
So you have to maintain a social distance
所以你要維持一個社會社交距離
That is in such a context
那是在這樣的一個脈絡下呢
just happened
才發生了剛剛
Let's start thinking about what we're talking about
我們我們說的五連得開始設想
The Syndrome Problem
這個結合病的問題
But despite this breakthrough in bacteriology
可是雖然有這個細菌學的這個突破
We just learned that bacterial contagion is conceivable
我們剛剛知道可以想像細菌的傳染
However, a later discovery was that
可是其實後來的一個發現是說
when you actually check
你真的去檢查的時候
just to test later
就是後來去驗
most people have germs
大部分人都有細菌
Most people have tuberculosis
大部分人都有結合感菌
in that era
在那個時代裡
just someone having a seizure
只是有人有發作
Someone didn't have a seizure
有人沒有發作而已
In fact, from this point of view
那其實從這角度來講
There is no reason why the person is sick
這個人沒有得病的原因
It's not that he hasn't been exposed to the combined strain.
並不是他沒有接觸到結合感菌
but to say
而是說
but other reasons
而是其他的原因
sorry i skipped a paragraph
對不起我跳過了一個段
I'll jump back and forth to talk about this passage
我跳我來回來講這一段
So the bacteria theory just now
所以剛剛那個細菌學說
The popularity of this concept
這個概念的流行
cause a lot of anxiety
就會引起很多人們的焦慮
a very famous anxiety
一個非常有名的焦慮
I'm here to tell you
我舉這邊跟大家講
it's about christianity
就是關於基督教領這個
The Common Chalice Controversy
共同聖餐杯的爭議
It's just that everyone knows
就是本來大家知道
When Christians receive the Holy Communion
基督教領的那個聖餐的時候
Why don't you just go up and drink in the same glass?
你不就上去同一個杯子裡喝酒嗎
right
對不對
This is the insurance of Jesus Christ
這是耶穌基督的保險
to all the zune brothers
就所有的祖內兄弟
Everyone also receives the insurance of Jesus Christ
大家同樣領受耶穌基督的保險
Then prove that you guys are brothers of Zune
然後證明你們是祖內的兄弟
But what?
可是呢
Now you just learned that fine pregnancy
你現在剛剛那個細孕學來了之後
Is there supposed to be on this cup?
這個杯子上是不是也應該有
Red dot, right?
紅點對不對
Then you see a man ahead
然後你看到前面有一個人
when you keep coughing
一直在咳嗽的時候
You start to suspect this Zoney brother
你就開始懷疑這個祖內兄弟
In fact, it will bring a big
其實事實上是會帶來很大的一個
dangerous
危險的
but if you don't drink because of it
但是如果你因此你就不喝的話
Wouldn't that be a clear violation
那豈不是很顯然是違背
Are the Zone brothers thinking right?
祖內兄弟的想法對不對
That is to say you are so out of touch
就是說你這麼見外
Make the people around you suspicious like this
這麼樣的把你身邊的人懷疑
he may be your relative
他可能就你的親人
So this is after you invented the fine pregnancy theory
所以這個是你在細孕學說發明之後
It caused a very big debate in the United States
就在美國引起了非常大的辯論
Should we reform this
究竟要不要改革這個
A reform seems to destroy an original symbolic meaning, right?
一改革就似乎就會破壞了一個本來的一個象徵意義對不對
mutual acceptance
人跟人之間共同領受
A ceremony of receiving insurance from the same cup
從同一個杯子的領受保險的一個儀式
but in the end
可是最後呢
By 1898
到了1898年
Two-thirds of U.S. dioceses vote to decide
美國三分之二的教區投票後決定
give up this chalice
放棄這個聖餐杯
can't use this cup anymore
不能再用這個杯子了
then change to
然後改成
change it to this
改成這樣子
Everyone has a small cup for everyone
就每個人有每個人的小杯
Everyone go up and get a glass
大家上去各領各的一杯
So you can see from this place that means
所以你從這個地方就可以看出就是說
After the general popularity of drama theory at that time
戲劇學說當時的普遍流行之後
People are very concerned about sharing a cup with others
人們對於跟別人共用一個杯子
share your drool
分享你的口水
An unprecedented sense of fear
產生了史無前例的一種恐懼感
even willing to pay such a high price
甚至願意付出這麼大的代價
destroy one of his symbolic meanings
都破壞了他的一個象徵意義
you have to change it
你都要把它改掉
then i just
那我剛剛
I just mentioned the next one from here
剛剛從這邊說我下面講的一個呢
says
是說
So everyone thought
所以大家本來想
Syndrome is clearly an infectious disease.
這樣結合病很明顯是個傳染病
but then it was
可是後來就是
It turns out that almost everyone actually has combined bacteria
結果發現幾乎每個人實際上都有結合菌
Someone wants to get over it and then it's okay
有人要得過了後來又好了
So it's obvious that
那所以很明顯就是說
This cannot be explained only by bacteria
這不是只用菌可以解釋得了的
So wait until that development from what we just talked about
所以等到從我們剛剛講的那個發展
By the time of the end of the nineteenth century
到了十九世紀末日事宜出的時候
people will think that in fact
人們會覺得其實
Whether you are sick or not
非結合究竟你發病與否
The key factor is not tuberculosis infection
關鍵的因素還不是結合感菌的傳染
but other issues
而是其他的問題
what is it like
像是什麼呢
like urbanization and industrialization
像是都市化工業化
Ventilation and lighting, malnutrition, working hours, etc.
通風採光 營養不良 工時等等
that is, the very poor
就是說是那些很窮的人
forced to live in terrible conditions
被迫住在很糟糕的環境裡
malnourished very poor
營養不良 非常牢类的人
they have poor resistance
他們抵抗力很差
So they have to combine bacteria
所以他們才得結合菌
So here's a classic in the history of medicine
所以這邊有一本醫學史的經典著作
叫The Making of a Social Disease
叫The Making of a Social Disease
is the first to be considered
就是這是第一個被認為
diseases caused by social factors
是因為社會因素而導致的疾病
is what we would have thought to say
就是我們剛本來會認為說
This Non-Combined Is an Infectious Disease
這非結合是一個傳染病
But now I realize
可是現在反而了解到
Actually you don't have to fully focus there
其實你不用完全聚焦在那裡
It is very important to say that your life
非常重要的是說你的生活上
Is it the one that has enough nutrients
它是否是那個有足夠的營養
If the environment it lives in is well ventilated and well lit
它住的環境如果通風採光很好化
In fact, it is not easy to be infected
其實它也不容易感染
There is also the issue of working hours
還有工時的問題
So the disease becomes a
所以這個病就變成一個
Instead, we have a turning point
我們反而等於有個轉折
What we learned is that
我們了解到的是說
state intervention
要國家的介入
For example, what we are talking about later
譬如說後來我們現在講的
work eight hours
工作八小時
also related to this
也跟這個有關
It's also related to this
就是也跟這個有關
And very strong like this picture you see
而且很強烈的像這個圖你看
It talks about making of social disease
它講說making of social disease
I think those who are sick are actually poor
就覺得得病的人其實都是窮人
They were forced to live in an industrial environment
他們被迫在工業化的環境裡
live in a crowded one
住在擁擠的一個
Places with poor ventilation and lighting
通風採光很差的地方
and that is to say bear
而且就是說承擔
long hours of work
很長時間的工作
That's why I'm sick
所以才生病
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講
To solve the core problem of the disease
要解決這個病的核心的問題
not to keep it from touching germs
不是讓它不要碰到細菌
It's about improving its living conditions
而是說要改善它的生活狀況
Especially give it enough nutrition and so on
特別是給它足夠的營養等等
On the contrary, do you think that if you are a farmer
那相對的反而你覺得說如果是農民
or those who live in the suburbs
或住在郊區的人
They don't actually get that much
他們其實不會得那麼多的
Not so easy to get tuberculosis
並不是那麼容易得到肺結核
And because of this, when he was recuperating from tuberculosis
也因此得肺結核療養的時候
Often go to the mountains or the sea to recuperate
常常都跑到山裡或海邊去進行療養
So the story I just told was
所以我剛剛講的故事是
Bacteriology
先從一個細菌學說
But then tuberculosis has
可是後來結核菌已經
Tuberculosis has been understood as a disease
結核病已經被了解成降了一個病
That is why this disease has become
那也因此這個病就變成說
Does the country improve
跟國家是否改善
The living environment of ordinary people is closely related to
一般人民的生活環境密切的相關
like Japan
比如像日本
He was originally unwilling to solve this problem by the country.
他本來國家也不願意來解決這個問題
Later, after the rise of communism
後來就是因為共產主義興起之後呢
As far as the Japanese government thinks
就日本政府才覺得說
must help
必須要來幫忙
people improve his workers
人們改善他的工人
Especially the worker improves his living environment
尤其是工人改善他的生活環境
Otherwise such a question
不然的話這樣的一個問題
would become a hotbed of communism
就會成為一個共產主義的溫床
That's the background of such a story
那這是這樣的一個故事的背景
Then everyone can think of saying
那大家一定可以想到說
If from this point of view
如果從這個角度來講
The second day of the 1924 season
1924季初二
China is definitely not an industrialized
中國絕對不是一個工業化
Or a very highly urbanized country, right?
或者說非常高度城市化的國家對不對
At that time it was said that more than 85% were farmers
那時候據說85%以上是農民
So logically speaking
所以照理講
He shouldn't have that much of a FJH problem.
他應該不會有那麼嚴重的費捷合問題
In fact, in the 19th century
那其實19世紀的時候
Quite a lot of this missionary classroom in China also said
有蠻多在中國的這個傳教室也都說
The Chinese don't look like Fei Jiehe's problem is too serious
中國人看起來好像費捷合的問題不太嚴重
there is such a saying
有這種說法
But then waited until after the 20th century
可是後來等到20世紀之後
they feel
他們覺得說
The problem of infectious diseases in China cannot be serious
中國傳染病的問題不可能不嚴重
Because I think they have a lot of bad habits
因為覺得他們有非常多的惡習
That even later China's own Anti-aging Association
那甚至於後來中國自己的防老協會
That is, Fei Jiehe was once translated as labor sickness
就是費捷合一度被翻譯成勞病
So it's the Anti-Age Society
所以是防老協會
They also use some statistics and estimates
他們也透過一些統計和估計
And to describe China as a Feijiehe problem
而把中國說成一個費捷合問題
very serious country
非常嚴重的一個國家
then he said
那他說
Combined disease is the deadliest disease in China
結合病是中國最致命的疾病
Then China is affected by the combined disease all over the world
那中國是全世界受到結合病
deepest cleansing country
清洗最深的國家
green and original
就感染綠而原
underground tuberculosis patients
地下的肺結核患者
And then the death rate is at least four times higher than in the UK
然後死亡率至少比英國高出四倍以上
is to create an image that is
就是創造出一個形象就是說
this problem is very serious
這個問題非常非常的嚴重
Even more serious than some industrialized countries
甚至比一些工業化的國家都來得嚴重的多
Even if you have heard
那甚至於大家如果聽過說
China is the sick man of East Asia
中國是東亞病夫的話
The imaginary disease should be tuberculosis
那個想像中的病應該就是肺結核
So from our point of view
所以從我們剛剛的角度來講
This should be a pretty strange thing
這應該是個蠻奇怪的事情
You are obviously a basically agricultural country
你明明是一個基本上農業國家
why you got one
為什麼你會得一個
In fact, if we look at the nineteenth century
其實我們如果看十九世紀的
For example, about tuberculosis in Japan
譬如說日本的那個結核病的話
It actually said it was low at the beginning
它其實一開始說是低的
It is because it rose after industrialization
是因為它工業化之後才上升
Then change after rising
然後上升之後再改
Only if there are worker sanitation workers will they drop again
再有工工衛生者才再下降
Logically speaking, you should be post-industrialized
照理講你應該是工業化之後
You are the only one affected by this disease
你才會受到這個病的侵擾
But at the time these
但是在當時呢這些
The prison association has created an understanding
房牢協會卻創造出了一個理解
That is to say, China is not only seriously
就是說中國不僅很嚴重
And maybe it's the worst country in the world
而且搞不好是世界上最嚴重的國家
In fact, in my research, there are
那其實我研究中有
I have looked at the stats they use
我有去看他們的所使用的統計
At that time, China had nothing to do with
那時候其實中國根本沒有相關
There are few relevant statistics
有的相關統計很少
In many other cases, the use of
其他很多時候是利用
For example, what is the one in Shanghai?
譬如說是什麼那個上海的
Concession in Shanghai
上海的租界啊
or some other zero-tax data pieced together
或者其他一些零稅的數據拼湊起來的
So from this point of view
那所以從這角度來講
It doesn't necessarily have solid statistics behind it.
這不見得背後有很紮實的統計資料
But they created such an image
但是他們卻創造出這樣一個形象
Maybe it's because I hope the government and compatriots will pay attention to it.
可能是因為希望政府和同胞重視吧
created a
就創造出了一個就是說
China has a very serious problem of combined disease
中國有很嚴重的結合病問題的
such a conclusion
這樣一個結論
but if you say that
那可是如果這樣講的話
then you clearly know
那你明明知道
The Western consensus at the time was that
西方當時的共識都認為
True Syndrome is very serious
真正結合病很嚴重
It must be related to industrialization and urbanization
一定是跟工業化都市化有關
you become to explain
你就變成要解釋
There is one that Mr. Zeng just mentioned
就有一個剛剛那個曾老師提到的
I call it the Chinese Syndrome Mystery
我稱之為中國結合病之謎
that is
就是說
Such a disease is understandable in Europe, America and Japan
這樣一個病在歐美和日本是可以理解的
Why in an agricultural society like China
為什麼在中國這樣的農業社會中
will cause so many
會造成這麼多的
they deeply hurt
他們深刻的傷害呢
It's like I can't understand
這樣就變成好像沒辦法理解了
right
對不對
then
那當時呢
they use these
他們用的這些
in the relevant researchers
在相關的研究者
To explain this phenomenon
為了解釋這個現象
proposed some very
提出了一些很
A very special explanation is that
很特殊的解釋就是說
whatever the cause of the disease
無論從疾病的成因
The population distribution of patients, etc.
病患的人口分布等等來看
Combined diseases in China are very different from those in the West
中國的結合病都非常不同於西方
And it has a unique Chinese characteristic
而有它獨特的一個中國特色
how to say
怎麼說呢
we now give an example
我們現在舉一個例子
study at the University of Chicago
就是留學芝加哥大學
Dr. Lai Daoyuan, who taught at Shanghai Medical College, said
認教於上海醫專的賴島原博士就說
Some people say that the amount of combined disease
有人說結合病的多寡
It is entirely related to the economic level of the people.
完全是跟國民的經濟程度有關的
as i just said
就我剛說的
It's a socioeconomic disease
這是一個社會經濟造成的疾病
So it's not at all
所以呢就根本都
All kinds of preventive work are irrelevant
各種預防工作無關痛癢
He said it was a close observation
他說這是一個貼面的觀察
Although many people say
雖然很多人這樣講
but i don't think it's a foregone conclusion
但我不認為這是一個定論
He said because
他說因為呢
What about us
我們呢
rich people in our country
我們國家裡有錢的人
Unlike American capitalists
跟美國資本家不同
like to get together
喜歡聚在一起
everyone is very
就大家在很
live close together, a lot of people get together
住得很近,很多人聚在一起
I don't talk, and I don't like doing outdoor activities
又不講,又不喜歡做戶外活動
And if you don't have the wind, the next generation is regarded as the standard of beauty
而且若不經風的臨代域被當成美人的標準
So that the chance of getting combined disease
所以以至於得結合病的機會
call poor people more
叫貧苦人家為多
The Great Disparity Between China and Foreign Countries
此中外懸殊之典
say what they think
就他們提出認為覺得說
Chinese people with sickness and morality are totally different from Westerners
中國的結合病的德的人跟西方人根本不一樣
Because people who get a lot are rich
因為得了很多是有錢的人
Because they have some really bad habits
因為他們有些特別糟糕的習慣
and cause them to get combined disease
而導致他們得了結合病
So he cites a statistic
所以他就舉一個統計資料
Patients with combined disease in Guangzhou
說廣州的結合病的患者
First-class patients accounted for 8.4%
頭等的病人佔8.4%
What about ordinary patients?
而一般的病人呢
That is, only 2% of civilians
就是平民只有2%
three times worse
差三倍
From this we can know that in China
由此可以知道在中國的情況下
why this happened
這個發生的原因
not economic factors
不是經濟因素
no nutritional factors
不是影響營養因素
but other factors
而是有別的因素
what about further
那進一步的呢
They also cite many
他們還引用了很多
Statistical reports on relevant clinical
就相關的臨床的統計報告
like this GA number
像這個GA號
The result of his research is that
他所做的研究的結果就是說
This is called Turbulic Losses in China
這邊叫Turbulic Losses in China
It is the combination of the lungs in China
就是肺結合在中國
His Beijing Indications Combination Diseases
他的北京主治結合病
10 years of this
長達10年的這個
Professor Ji Huanghao pointed out that
季篁號教授就指出說
The real thing is that everyone in China has
真正的在中國人大家得
The cause of combination disease is not what we just talked about
結合病的原因不是我們剛剛講的
those socioeconomic and nutritional factors
那些社會經濟和營養的因素
but unhygienic habits
而是不衛生的習慣
Chinese habits will inevitably lead to a sense of integration
就中文的習慣必然導致結合感
Take a wide walk in the family
就在家庭內廣為散步
Small hotel at home or in the village
在家裡或是村莊的小旅館
Both sick and healthy people sleep on the same bed
病人和健康人都睡在同一個康上
It's just that they sleep too close
就是他們睡得太近了
and then the second one
然後第二個呢
Whether at home, office or on the street
無論在家裡公務場所或大街上
habit of spitting
隨地吐痰的習慣
not only taken for granted
不僅被大家視為理所當然
and very common
而且非常普遍
So this is the habit of talking about spitting
所以這是講到吐痰的習慣
What about the third one?
第三個呢是說
After picking up food from the shared game
從大家共用的玩理夾了食物之後
The chopsticks are delivered directly to everyone's mouth
筷子就直接送到每個人的嘴裡
So this is talking about communal food
所以這講的是共食製
That is, if there is a large bowl in the middle
就是說如果有個大碗在中間
Your chopsticks go in to catch the cold
你的筷子进去夹冷
you put it in your mouth
你就放在你的嘴巴里
So if you have tuberculosis
所以如果你得了肺结核
After next time you send your germs to the bowl
下一次之后你就把你的病菌送到碗里
Then eat it for someone else
然后给别人吃进去了
So he imagined it was because of your family
所以他想象中是因为你们家里的
There are so many unhygienic habits at home
在家里有这么多的不卫生的习惯
so lead to
所以导致了
say this disease
就说这个疾病的
special one popular
特别的一个流行
And another reason
而且另外一个原因呢
It's just that your family is very big
就是你们的家庭又非常的大
you are very many
你们人非常多
And the way we get along is too intimate
而且相处的方法又过度的亲密
He said that in China not only parents
他说在中国不仅父母
even grandparents
就连祖父母
Boshu Uncle and other male elder relatives
伯淑 舅父等男性长辈亲戚
Gu Yi Shen
孤仪审
Mother-in-law, aunt and other female elder relatives
审婆 舅妈等女性长辈亲戚
Cousins, brothers, sisters, and other relatives of the same generation
堂表 兄弟 姐妹等平辈亲戚
And the servants have very close contact with children.
还有仆人都跟儿童有非常亲密的接触
So what this imagines is that
所以这想象中的就是说
in a very large family
一个非常大的家庭里
many people in close proximity
非常多人密切地在一起
Spread of disease as a result of communication
交流的结果而导致疾病的流传
But in fact at that time very
可是其实那时候非常
Chinese people are not all big families
中国人并不是都是大家庭
there are a lot of people
有非常多的人
there are a lot of single people
有非常多单身的人
So this is actually a
所以这其实也是一个
A problematic description of a Chinese family at that time
有問題的一個對當時中國家庭的一個描述
But it also constituted the epidemiologist at that time
但是也是構成了這個流行病學家當時
considered a major reason the disease was transmitted in China
認為這個疾病在中國傳遞的一個主要原因
Okay, so from that point of view we take it back
好 所以從這角度來講我們拿回來
As I just said, at the beginning of the 20th century
跟剛剛我說的在二十世紀初的時候
The mainstream thinks that Fei Jie is compared with Chen Yin
主流的認為費傑和陳寅的來相比
becomes a great contrast
就成為很大的對比
That is to say, Westerners at that time
就是說那時候西方人
or the predecessor of the then United Nations
或當時的聯合國的前身
The Ministry of Health of the League of Nations has always emphasized that Fei Jiehe is a Social Disease
國聯的衛生部都一直強調費傑和是一個Social Disease
But in the context of China
但是在中國的脈絡中
It has turned into a Family Disease
它有變成一個Family Disease
based on family
是以家庭為單位
And a disease that spreads in the family
而在家庭裡傳播的一個病
It does not stem from industrialization and urbanization
它不是源於工業化與都市化
And the representative patients are not poor
而且代表性的病人也不是窮人
Instead, they are rich people in big families who live a traditional life
反而是過著傳統生活大家庭裡的富人
So it's not a social disease
那所以這不是一個社會性的疾病
but a family disease
而是一個家庭性的疾病
And it's a disease unique to a Chinese family
而且是一個中國家庭特有的疾病
This is equivalent to one of the
這等於是當時的一個
an important consensus
一個重要的一個共識
That
那
I'm thinking when you're listening now
我在想大家現在聽的時候
Do you think it's a bit
會不會覺得這有點
far-fetched or unimaginable
牽強或難以想像
people at that time would come like this
當時的人會這樣子來
Conceive your place
構想說你這個地方
The reason next door is different from the whole world
隔壁的原因跟全世界都不太一樣
But it was indeed a
可是當時的確是一個
public health experts
被很多公衛專家
Even very credible public health experts
甚至是非常有公信力的公衛專家所
an idea promoted
提倡的一個想法
For example, here is a
譬如說現在這邊有一位是
Female public health pioneers who once studied at Yale
曾經留學耶魯的女性公衛先驅
Ge Chenghui
叫葛成慧
She's sick in her Chinese with combination
她在她的中國人與結合病
just talk about the Chinese
就討論中國人
The relationship between Chinese people and combined disease
中國人跟結合病的關係
point out that the Chinese people have the above bad habits
就指出中國人因為有上面那些惡習
So what?
所以說呢
so that only one family member
如此一來只要一個家庭成員
contracted disease
染上結合病
before long
要不了多久
Half the family is a victim
家中一半的人都成了受害者
Therefore, in the past, combined disease was called a master.
因而過去將結合病稱之為傳師喔
I give this example to say
我舉這個例子就是說
what do you see her image like
你看她的形象是什麼
this is not a society
這不是一個社會
but to say
而是說
It was spread at home, right?
是在家裡傳播的對不對
someone got it
有一個人得了呢
soon everyone will have
很快大家都得
And what about this matter
而且這個事情呢
The Chinese knew it before
中國人以前就知道了
Because there is another person named Xijia in Chuanshilao.
因為傳師牢另外一個名叫喜嘉
Xijia disease
喜嘉病
So he especially emphasized the word
所以他特別來強調這個詞
It's the prison
就是傳師牢
it's actually interesting
這件事其實很有趣
Because at that time in fact
因為在那個時期其實
That western doctor advocates the abolition of traditional Chinese medicine.
那個西醫都是主張要廢止中醫的
They hate using
他們非常厭惡使用
traditional Chinese medicine vocabulary
這種傳統的中醫詞彙
Then why do you specifically use a
那為什麼你特別反而用一個
this looks like a weird
這看起來一個很奇怪的
very strange word
很奇怪的詞
It's especially interesting
就特別值得玩味
a little bit reveals
一點點就可以透顯出
Katsuragi would very much like to take advantage of an original
葛城會非常想利用一個原來的
old vocabulary
舊的詞彙
to inspire everyone to a
來激發大家對於一種
inside the whole family
整個家庭裡面
the disease spread
這個病流傳
And an image that causes people to die
而導致人們都死掉的一個形象
The prison is
傳師牢是
Passing on the master prison is a kind of prison disease
傳師牢是牢病的一種
This concept probably appeared around the seventh century
這概念大概出現在七世紀左右
That basically reflects that
那基本上就可以反映說
The Chinese at that time already knew
那時候的中國人已經知道
this
這個
Tuberculosis is contagious
肺結核是可以傳染的
But what about their theory?
可是他們提出來的理論呢
Let's pass on the prison
我們就傳師牢
That is, after one person dies
就是說有一個人死掉之後
And then the worm after he died
然後牢蟲在他死掉之後
leave his body
離開他的身體
and ran to his family
然後跑到他家人的身上
So later lead to the family
所以後來導致家人
Others contracted the disease and died
其他人感染這個病而死亡
So everyone sounds like this, don't you think?
那大家這樣聽起來是不是覺得
It seems to be a bit like combined bacteria, right?
好像跟結合感菌有點像對不對
There is also an entity
也是有一個實體
just called a prison bug
只是叫做牢蟲
and spread in the family
而且在家庭裡面傳播
so you take the word out
那所以你把這個詞拿出來
It seems to make others feel that
好像讓人別人覺得說
In fact, this disease in China is a family disease.
其實中國這個病是家庭疾病的事
The Chinese Prison already knew
中文牢早就知道了
Words like this were even coined before
以前甚至有這樣的詞創造出來
to describe this thing
來描述這個事情
And use this word to make everyone reinforce that
而且用這個詞讓大家強化那種
An image that feels like the disease is spreading in the family
覺得這個病在家庭裡傳播的一個形象
But what?
可是呢
if we think about it
如果我們仔細想一想
Prison worms and combined infectious bacteria
傳世牢的牢蟲跟結合感菌
Behavioral patterns between
兩者之間的行為模式
It's actually very different
其實是很不一樣的
how to say
怎麼說呢
I didn't just tell you that
我剛剛不是跟大家說那個
The worm in the handed down prison is born after death
傳世牢的牢蟲是在人死後
just run away, right?
才跑掉嘛 對不對
But we save fuel and get infected with bacteria when we are actually alive
可是我們節油感菌其實是在活著的時候
passed on while alive
活著的時候傳過去的
So according to Academician Liang Qizi and
所以根據那個梁啟資院士和
Research by Mr. Li Jianmin of Shi Yisuo
史以所的李建民老師的研究
The reason why the concept of the so-called master is the most popular
所謂傳師這個概念最有傳的原因
In fact, it is a Buddhist or Taoist concept.
其實是一個佛教或者說一個道教的概念
It means that in a family
意思就是說一個家族裡面
your father's eg your karma
你的父親的譬如說你的業報
Your karma will be transmitted equal to
你的業報會傳等於
Gekqua passed down to others in the family
蓋誇傳授的傳給家庭的其他的人
It's actually kind of like an inheritance
這其實有點像遺產
Do you understand what I mean?
大家了解我的意思嗎
That is to say, you have a lot of karma
就是說本來你有很多業報
Maybe the merit you do and your karma
可能你做的功德和你的業報
on your dad
在你爸爸的身上
Your dad's passing only this all goes to
你爸爸的過世只有這全部都傳到
on your next generation
你下一代的身上
Nao Chongzhi is just a part of it
那勞崇植其中的一個一環而已
In other words, the transmission process
換句話說這個傳的過程
In fact, it is related to the concept of religion.
其實是跟這個宗教的概念有關的
not because you live together
而不是說因為你們住在一起
but now
可是現在呢
So from this point of view
就是所以從這角度來講
Katsuragi Hui he re-established the family and disease
葛城慧他是重新建立了家庭跟疾病的
a relation through the word
一個關聯透過這個詞
He mentioned the life-saving
他提起傳世道的這個救命
to highlight family members
是為了凸顯家庭成員
The horrible situation of widespread labor sickness
普遍感染勞病的那種恐怖的情形
But the concept of home
可是其實家的概念
There has been a conversion
那這邊已經有轉換了
He highlights that it is indeed family
他凸顯的確是家庭
is a new one family concept
是一個新的一個家庭概念
relationship with disease
跟疾病的關係
It's not about the religious
不是講那個宗教性的就是說
A transmission of merit and karma
功德跟業報的一個傳遞
It's about family members being together
而是說家庭成員因為共處一事
Intimate interaction day and night
朝夕相處親密互動
causing a disease to spread
而造成了一個疾病流傳
So it's kind of like saving old and new from Pingzhuang
所以這有點像是救平莊新舊
right
對不對
On the one hand, it makes you feel a sense of fear
一方面讓你感覺到恐懼感
On the other hand, I changed it to something
二方面有把它換了一個東西
So what? The family has grown from a religious-ethical organization
那所以呢家庭已經從一個宗教倫理的組織
become a physical cohabitation
變成一個物質性的共同居所
But from these places you will see
可是從這些地方你會看得出
That is to say, he advocated this life-saving
就是說他提倡這個救命
is key for highlighting, festival and dissemination
是為了凸顯、費節和傳播的關鍵
family in china
就在中國的家庭
So and in fact in
所以而且事實上在
After the concept became popular
在這個概念流行之後
let's see that
我們看那個
Just like now sometimes our teachers
就像現在有時候大家老師們
Don't know what students write their experience?
不知道同學們寫心得嗎
Nafang Primary School invites many students
那房小學會邀請很多學生
to write articles
來寫的文章
many students started
就有很多學生開始
with a look of fear
用一種充滿恐懼的眼光
looking at his parents and grandparents
看著他的父母跟祖父母
and say i can feel
然後就說我可以感覺到
the way my grandfather ate or spit
我祖父吃東西或者是吐痰的方式
and then how to pass it on to my grandmother
然後怎麼傳遞給我祖母
And later killed my brothers and sisters
然後後來害了我的兄弟姐妹
I just feel an unprecedented
就是感覺到一種史無前例的就是說
you by these
你被這些
are you at home
你在家裡
This is your dearest person
本來這是你最親愛的人
but you feel
可是你反而感覺到
They passed the disease on to you
他們把這個病傳遞給你
Then you can't protect yourself from a sense of fear
然後你沒辦法保護你自己的一種恐懼感
That was a very common feeling at that time
那是那個時候一個很普遍的一個感受
good
好
So from this point of view you see
那所以從這角度來講你看
it's really a very different
這真的是一個非常不同的
understanding of a disease
對於一個疾病的理解
in China in the 1930s
就是在1930年代的中國
People Don't Think Syndrome Is Industrialization
人們自不認為結合病是工業化
caused by urbanization
和都市化所造成的
If so, it is a process of modernization
若是的話這是一個現代化的歷程
In fact in combination disease is understood as
事實上在結合病被理解為
We feel it when Social disease
Social disease的時候我們就覺得它
would be considered a disease of civilization
就是會被認為是一個文明病
disease caused by civilization
是文明造成的病
But at that time the Chinese believed that
可是當時中國人比較認為
Nor do they see the state as actively involved in
他們也不認為國家積極介入
can solve this problem
可以解決這個問題
So you won't learn Japanese like
所以你不會學習日本一樣
I think the government needs to intervene
覺得說要政府介入
In fact, the government cannot
其實政府也沒有能力
to solve this problem
來解決這個問題
what about the opposite
那相反的呢
in Chinese understanding
在中國的理解中
this disease
這個病
including even public health officials
包括即便是公衛官員
and all things think
和有事之事都認為
The Culprit of Syndrome in China
中國結合病的罪魁禍首
in a traditional Chinese family
是傳統中國家庭中
long-term unhygienic
長期養成的不衛生的
a personal habit
一個個人習慣
So this is how to understand the disease
所以是這樣來理解這個病
becomes quite the opposite
就變得很相反了
understood from the west
從西方理解
This is caused by modernization
這是現代化造成的
understood in Chinese
在中國理解成說
Because you are too present in a traditional family
因為你太現在傳統的家庭中
you have this disease
你才得這個病
So although you are not industrialized
所以你雖然沒有工業化
but you get very sick with this
但你得這個病得非常多
That even some public health experts pointed out
那甚至於有公衛專家指出
The ultimate solution to the combined disease in China
中國結合病的最終解決
Know that it is a small family that fully adopts Europe and the United States
知道是全面採納歐美的小家庭
Then this may be better than the dining table we just talked about
那這可能比我們剛剛講的那個餐桌
more amazing
更驚人
That is to say, in order to solve a disease
就是說你為了解決一個病
you have to change
你要改出
You want everyone's family system to change
你要人家家庭制度都發生改變
but you can feel it
可是你就可以感覺到就是說
At that time, public health experts thought
當時那種公衛專家覺得
with their understanding of the disease
以他們的了解這個病
How many reasons for its establishment are related to
成立的原因有多少是跟
related to the family environment
這個家庭環境有關的
If we speak in more abstract language
那我們若用比較抽象的語言來講的話
we can say
我們可以說
This is called the pathologicalization of the traditional Chinese family
這叫做傳統中國家庭的病理化
as you think
就你覺得
You imagine this home as the cause of all kinds of diseases
你把這個家想像成種種疾病的起因
Then there's the harm it brings to everyone
然後就是說帶給大家的傷害
So it should have been a
那所以本來應該是一個
All of your values, right?
你的價值的全員對不對
you get warm
你得到溫暖
place of warmth and hugs
溫暖和擁抱的地方
You now feel like it's the source of all your problems
你現在反而覺得它是一切問題的源頭
is a like a cause
是一個像一個病因一樣
Pathologicalization of a Traditional Family
一個傳統家庭的病理化
That's the point at that time
那這是那個當時的關
A conclusion drawn on disease
在疾病方面得到的一個結論
I'm talking here, do you have any questions?
我講到這裡大家有沒有什麼問題
Ruiyou can first propose
瑞友可以先提出一下
please
請
This has something to do with the noble family, is it in the noble family?
這跟貴族家庭有關是在貴族家庭嗎
Um
嗯
that red chinchilla
那紅龍貓
yes
是
right
對
For this noble family, it is a stump
對這貴族家庭裡面是殘角
The topic of remnants
殘角的這個議題
right
對
Like I mentioned the adjacent generation domain just now?
像剛剛有提到臨代域嘛
so you asked this question, right?
所以您問到這個問題對不對
What he meant was that
他講的這個意思就是說
From a certain point of view, the environment of this disease
某個角度來講得這個病的環境
In fact, there is something in that culture
其實那個文化中有點
one that would have encouraged people
本來就鼓勵人們的一個
caused by the lifestyles that people are encouraged to adopt
鼓勵人們採取的生活形態造成的
Then what you just said he didn't talk about the remnants
那你剛剛講的他倒沒有講到殘族
just say you don't like doing outdoor activities
只講說你不喜歡做戶外活動
this is one of the important points
這是其中很重要的一點
For example, another point is to say
那譬如說另外有一點就是說
He'll keep emphasizing like I just didn't say
他會一直強調說像我剛剛不講
western opinion says
西方認為說
The problem to be solved in anatomical diseases is the problem of lighting
解剖病要解決的問題就是採光的問題
right
對不對
But relatively speaking
可是相對來講
China has always been afraid of the wind
中國一直都很怕風
The doors and windows are tightly closed
門窗位關得很緊
I don't want to go outside
那不願意往外面走
This is what was said more
這是當時講的比較多的
silkworm feet to no direct connection there
蠶足到沒有直接連接到那裡
Um
嗯
in
其中
because it is
因為就是
Hakka is you
客家是你
they are you
他們客家是你
they are all dame of labor
他們都是勞動的女爵士
often done in agricultural products
常常在農品裡面做
right
對
yes
是
then we
那我們
Speaking of Song and Ming Dynasties
講宋明
right
對
Three Canons of Lecturers
講家的三個典內
They are all Hakka dames
他們都是客家的女爵士
yes
是
are playing and teaching abroad
都是在國外奏教
When the Republic of China came out of the clouds
在民國出雲的時候
yes
是
they go all the way
他們一路走來
Lecture Committee
講受委員會
dame outside a foreign country
國外以外的女爵士
yes
是
I will later
待會我會
He will appear in this story later
待會這個故事裡會出現他
you wait a moment
您稍微等一下
right
對
Then I just stopped here to tell you
那我剛剛在這邊跟大家停一下是說
The stories I just told you are all about a public health expert.
我剛剛跟大家講的故事全部是一個公衛專家的故事
right
對不對
And everyone can hear that it was actually the
而且大家可以聽得出來其實是當時的
Working in China
在中國工作
Medical elites at home and abroad
國內外的醫療精英
But they came to a very surprising conclusion
但他們得到一個非常令人意外的結論
That is to say, this is a very serious problem.
就是說這是個非常嚴重的問題
But Chen Yin is completely different from the West
但陳寅跟西方完全不一樣
And this Chen Yin directly came from
而且這個陳寅直接源到
A condition of the family originating in China
源自於中國的家庭的一個狀況
That's why I said that in the West it is regarded as a
那所以我說在西方被當成一個
social disease
社會疾病
Treated as a family disease in China
在中國被當成一個家庭疾病
put it in the history of medicine
那這放在醫學史裡
is a very surprising thing
是個非常令人意外的事情
Because logically speaking, they have also received this training.
因為照理講他們也都有受過這個訓練
And everyone just saw the Lai Dou I cited
而且大家剛剛看到我引的賴豆
His first sentence is
他第一句就是說
In China, this problem should not only be an economic problem
在中國這個問題應該不只是經濟問題
Indicates that he knows that the world believes that
表示他知道世界各地都認為
It's a socioeconomic issue, right?
這是社會經濟的問題對不對
But we are such a one that puts all the problems
可是我們這樣一個把所有的問題
It all belongs to China, this belongs to the family
都歸於中國的這個歸於家庭這一點
Surprising words in medical treatment
放在醫療裡面很令人意外的話
But if we put him in
可是如果我們把他放在
Modern Chinese History in the 20th Century
二十世紀的中國現代史
or modern history
或近代史
I am the director of the modern history of the surrounding
我是那個周圍遠近代史的所長
That is, if we break away from medical
就是我們如果脫離醫療
put him in the mainstream of modern history
把他放到現代史的主流的話
In fact it's common sense
事實上這是常識
that's the one
就是這是一本那個
This is a book written by Susan Glasser
這是一個這個書是 Susan Glasser 寫的
It's called Transfusions of Family and State
叫做 Transfusions of Family and State
Let’s talk about how people in modern China regard this family
就講現代中國的人們對於這個家
Some visions and ideas of the country
跟國的一些願景和想法
It is written in this book that at that time
這本書裡面就寫說在當時
In fact, whether it is the Kuomintang or the Communist Party
其實不論是國民黨共產黨
Or journalistic campaigners
或者說新聞化運動者
Everyone thinks the problem is with the family
大家都認為問題出在家庭
Feeling that family is at the heart of the problem
覺得家庭是問題的一個核心
So what I just told you is that
所以我剛剛跟大家講的是說
From the perspective of medical history, we
我們從醫療史的角度來講
It's surprising how you came to this conclusion
這很令人意外你怎麼得到這個結論
But if you're out of medical history
可如果你但脫離醫療史
you go back to that big social environment
你回到那個大的社會環境中
Everyone already felt the problem
本來大家就已經覺得問題
It's all about the family
全部都出在家庭的身上了
you know what i mean
大家了解我的意思
Then I will give you the most drastic example
那我給大家一個最激烈的例子
The most intense is Fu Sinian
最激烈的就是傅思年
His first issue in Xinchao
他在新朝的創刊號
You see, this is also the first issue
你看這也是創刊號
publish an article
發表一篇文章
called the root of all evil
叫做萬惡之源
He said that China is the root of all evil
他就說中國的萬惡之源
is a Chinese family
就是中國的家庭
In fact, we rarely get this
其實我們很少受到這個
At that time it was
那個時候這是
very harsh criticism
批判的非常的激烈
Then why did he say
然後為什麼他說
The Chinese family is the root of all evil in China
中國的家庭是中國的萬惡之源呢
He said that because Chinese families are
他說因為中國的家庭就是
The biggest force that destroys personality
破壞個性的最大的勢力
what does that mean he said
這什麼意思呢他說
from the day the child was born
從孩子生下來的那一天
teach him how to be tough
就教訓他如怎樣硬實
how to deny yourself
怎樣舍己從人
how to be your father and mother's son
怎樣做你爹娘的兒子
never teach him to do
絕對不肯教他做
his being himself
他的做自己的自己
so it's a lot like your kid
所以這很像你的孩子
not one of your children
不是你的孩子的一個
The version from a hundred years ago, right?
一百年前的版本對不對
He just said don't teach him to catch himself
他就講說不教他抓自己
In a word it is
一句話來講就是
extreme destruction of personality
極力的摧殘個性
So he felt that the root of all evil
所以他覺得萬惡根源
It means that after you destroy a person's personality
意思就是說你摧殘一個人的個性之後
All the above questions come from here
上面所有的問題都從這裡來的
because the person has lost autonomy
因為這個人失去了自主性
with his individuality
跟他的一個個體性
what about in this article
那在這篇文章裡呢
He thinks the key is family
他認為關鍵就在於家庭
destroy personality
摧殘個性
But what?
可是呢
In this article, his personalities are put in quotation marks more than a dozen times
這文章裡他十幾次個性全部都放在這個引號裡
So he knows full well the word is new
所以他充分的知道這個詞是個新詞
At that time, people didn't know what personality was
那個時候人還不曉得什麼叫個性
because why
因為為什麼呢
Because including individuals and individuals are actually new words just created
因為包括個人跟個體其實都是剛剛才創造的新詞
It's from Japanese, it's the translation
是來自日文是翻譯那個
individual and individualism have just been introduced
individual跟individualism才剛剛引入的詞
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講
That Fussian critique of the Chinese family
那個富斯年對於中國家庭的批判
from a libertarian individualistic standpoint
就源於一個自由主義的個人主義的立場
Absolutely in this original home setting
絕對在這個原來的家庭環境中
Don't let children decide what industry they want to go
不讓小孩自己決定自己要走的行業
If you don't let him get married, you have to listen to the family's orders.
不讓他結婚什麼事都要聽家庭的
so that he loses one of his autonomy as an individual
以至於他喪失他作為個體的一個自主性
let him call it a personality
讓他稱之為個性
So that's a source of his critique
所以這是他批判的一個源頭
That's called the root of all evil
那這叫做萬惡之源
There are many criticisms in that book from this angle.
那那個書裡還有很多都是從這個角度來批判的
Even Hu Shi, the dean of the month
甚至像那個本月的院長胡適
He said that China used to feel the most unfilial
他有講說中國以前覺得最不孝
That means you are not filial to your grandfather, right?
就是說你不孝你的祖父對不對
unfilial offspring
不孝子孫
He said that even if you are not filial, you will make progress
他說就算不孝才會有進步
From the perspective of evolution, there is no way to progress without mutation
從演化來講沒有變異就沒有辦法進步
So it's good for everyone to be unfilial
所以大家不孝是好的
it was one of those days
就是這是當時的一個
such a critical position
一個這樣的一個批判的一個立場
So let's look at it from this point of view
那所以說我們現在從這角度來看
Actually we have a puzzle
其實我們有一個謎題
That's why two sports that look so different
就是為什麼兩個看起來很不同的運動
It seems like we have a date
好像有約好了一樣
It's the science-based Fei Jiehe's prevention and control campaign
就是基於科學的費捷合的防治運動
I use the picture of Katsuragi Club as a representative
我用葛城會的圖作代表
make it easier for everyone to remember
讓大家比較容易記得
and this individualistic
和這個基於個人主義
Seems like a home improvement movement based on an ideology
好像基於一個意識形態的家庭改造運動
They seem to have made an appointment, right?
他們好像相約好了約好了一樣對不對
They all think the problem is the same regardless
他們都認為問題不論而同的
Seeing the Chinese family as the root of the problem
把中國家庭視為問題的根源
serious personal harm
對個人帶來的重大的傷害
On Katsuragi's side, right?
在葛城會這邊對不對
It's the family that passed the disease on to this young man.
是家庭就是把病傳給這個年輕人
a student an individual
一個學生一個個人
I just said that many young students feel
我剛剛說很多年輕學生都覺得
They saw their body's being grandpa
他們看到了自己的身體的被祖父
a threat from a grandfather or father
祖父或父親的一個威脅
what about here
那在這裡呢
In the year of Fuji, it is also said that they were all killed by their parents.
富士年也講都是被父母害的
destroy your personality
就摧殘你的個性
Why is this one derived from the scientific
為什麼這一個源自於科學的
with a value derived from society
跟一個源自社會的一個價值觀
It seems that two people are walking together
好像兩個人走在一起
right
對不對
as if supporting each other
好像相互支持一樣
Is this a coincidence
這是巧合嗎
if it is not a coincidence
如果不是巧合的話
What is the mechanism behind the difference?
不如而同的背後是什麼機制呢
I'm talking about do you have any friends here?
我講到這裡有沒有朋友
any ideas
有什麼想法
Because it looks really close, right?
因為看起來真的很相近對不對
is that a coincidence
那這是巧合嗎
you want to say please say
你要說請說
please i want to ask
請問我想要請問一下就是
And about the house behind it is
而關於背後房子是
I mean after World War II
我所指的到二戰之後
or card interface
還是卡介面的
That is, the Allied Forces keep pushing
也就是盟軍不斷推訪
Whether it is Japan or
無論是日本還是
Dongdong has already
東東當中都已經
Because of BCG to treat
因為卡介苗去治療
In the case of National Taiwan University Hospital
當時以台大醫院來講
he will go to therapy
他會去治療
They had a lot of medical students at the time
他們當時的醫學生分子很多
Including treatment with convalescence
包含用療養的方式去治療
BCG
包含用卡介苗
and treatment with Feijie and toxin
還有用費傑和毒素去治療
But they all belong to the family structure of Confucian society
但是一樣都是屬於儒家社會的家庭結構
As a result we can learn one thing
結果我們可以得知一件事情
That is to say, local Chinese
就是說中國當地
Although they bring the problem home
雖然他們把問題歸納成家裡
But Fei Jie and the problem is still serious
但是費傑和問題還是嚴重
Based on the medical data in Taiwan at that time
以台灣當時的醫療數據來講
Hygienic habits in Taiwan at that time
台灣當時的衛生習慣
running water etc
自來水等等都已經
Popular in several provinces of leading China
普及於領先中國好幾個省份
even at the level of an itch
甚至是在領頭癢的水準
But he Feige and the problem is still serious
但是他費傑和問題還是嚴重
so i personally think
所以我個人認為
you take your problems home
你把問題歸就在家
Or use it as Confucianism
或者說把它用成儒家思想
or problematic points in feudal thought
或封建思想的當中的問題點
I think a little bit at the time
我覺得有一點點在當時來講
Hua Po fallacy
應該是一種華頗謬論
What
什麼
a Huapo fallacy
一種華頗謬論
that is to say a
就是說一種
how to explain
該怎麼解釋呢
is a fallacy
就是一種謬論
everyone is one of a kind
大家就是一種
everyone thinks
大家都覺得
It's the whole problem. All problems boil down to this
是整個問題 所有問題都歸納成這樣
Even if everyone has no money today
哪怕今天是大家沒錢
Or everyone has no culture
或者是大家沒有文化
It's all because of family
都是因為家的關係
So I think it's a time
所以我覺得這是一個當時
No matter what the New Culture Movement says
無論是新文化運動來講的話
At that time, everyone had a trend
當時大家帶著一個風向
so is it a coincidence
那它是不是一個巧合
I think it was some intellectuals at that time
我覺得就是當時一些有知識的份子
Some people like Cai Peihuo sum it up as
像蔡培伙那一些人把它歸納成
Inductive result
歸納的結果啦
But as for the cost, it was finally because of BCG
但至於當費節合最後是因為卡介苗
fully treated
才被治療完整的
so i feel like saying
所以我會覺得說
If it can be classified as a family problem
如果把它歸納成家裡的問題的話
I think it's still a little biased
我覺得還是有一點點偏頗
But I don't know what professor you think
但是我不知道教授您是怎麼想的
about this one thing
對 這一件事情
Yes, first you gave a very important background
是 首先你講了一個很重要的背景
That’s what we just said, only the germ theory, right?
就是我們剛剛講的只有細菌學說對不對
But there is no cure
可是其實沒有療法
As far as the time I am talking about is
就我現在講的一個時間是
there is no cure at all
根本沒有辦法治療的
just like you said
就是像您所講的一樣
So back then it was actually just a nursing home
所以那時候其實只有療養院
that is no effective therapy
那也是沒有有效的療法
So this question is another very important background
所以這題又是一個很重要的背景
in this story
在這個故事中
Then another big difference
那然後另外一個很大的差別
actually
其實
I just had no chance to speak
我剛剛比較沒有機會講
That is to say, in the context of Japan just now
就是說在日本剛剛的脈絡中
Have treated it as a Social Disease
已經把它當成是一個Social Disease
right
對不對
like i said
就像我講的就是說
So that later the Japanese royal family began
以至於後來日本皇室開始
is to provide a large fund
就是提供了一個很大的基金
To solve the problem of Japanese workers
要來解決日本工人的
This puzzling and problematic thing for workers
工人的這個費解和問題的事
would feel like saying
就會覺得說
you improve its nutrition
你改善它的營養
improve its living environment
改善它的居住環境
might help it
可能會對它有幫助
You treat it like a Social Disease
你把它當成一個Social Disease
to deal with
來處理
Well, today this is in the context of China
那今天這個在中國這個脈絡裡
I just because of that time
我剛剛因為那個時間
What I didn't say carefully is
我沒有仔細講的是
Actually at that time
其實當時
The one who was taken by Xiehe Hospital
被協和醫院的那個
a very important leader
一個很重要的一個領導人
His name is John Grant
他叫John Grant
is listed as one of the John Hopkins
是被列為John Hopkins的一個
public health hero
公衛英雄
he just said
他就說
Let's not prioritize combination disease
我們不要優先處理結合病
Because if he's Social Disease
因為如果他是Social Disease的話
It just requires the government to invest a lot of money
就是需要政府提投資很多的錢
to improve the financial environment
來改善設金環境
if that doesn't work
如果這樣就解決不了了
So in fact our story
所以其實我們這個故事
how much is in that environment
多少是在那個環境下
you think you can't help
你覺得你沒辦法幫
if you think about it
如果你把它想到
into a social disease
成一個social disease
everyone helpless
大家都束手無策
Then if you emphasize it as a
那如果你把它強調是一個
unhygienic habits
不衛生的習慣
words that cause disease
導致的疾病的話
at least we can do something
至少大家可以做一些事
So it's kind of in this vein
所以有點是這個脈絡中
what happened
所發生的
So you said that is not to say
那你說那個是不是就是說
slightly incorrect
有點有點不正確
This story is now undeniably incorrect
這個故事現在毫無疑問是不正確
So from what we say today
所以從我們今天講出來講
Fei Jie and Qi is a respiratory disease
費傑和齊是一個呼吸性的疾病
right
對不對
not at all through this
根本不是透過這個
That is to say, the situation of droplet infection
就是說飛沫傳染的狀況
So the concept is
所以這個概念在
From today's point of view
從今天角度來講
scientifically incorrect
科學上是不正確
but people at that time
可是當時的人
It is the leading scientist we are talking about
就是我們講的這個 leading scientist
Like the Wuliande I just mentioned
像我剛剛講的五連德
he always believed it
他一直相信這一點
so he
所以他
He's even a nominee over there
他甚至是那邊有講的提名人
he will think
他都會認為說
this
這個
We're going to treat it like a disease like this
我們要把它當成這樣一個疾病來處理
So from the people at that time
所以從當時人來講
they will think
他們會認為
Actually this is the question I just asked
其實這是我剛剛問的問題
At that time, people may think that
當時人來講他們可能覺得
Scientists at the time
當時的科學家來講
they may feel
他們可能覺得
It's the best they can have
這是他們可以擁有的最好的做法
and has the most evidence
而且有最多的證據
The display should face this direction
顯示應該朝向這個方向
But the problem is that this is at the same time
可是問題是這個是同時
In fact, it is also related to a large social and cultural environment
其實也跟一個大的社會文化環境
closely related
密切的相關
Are they under his influence?
究竟他們有沒有受到他的影響
it's a question I posed
就是我提出來的一個問題
I think what you just said was that
那我想你剛剛講的是覺得
maybe there is no way to say
可能有是不是可以這樣說
that's how you feel, don't you
你是這樣感覺是不是
Do you have any other friends or want to say something here?
有沒有別的朋友或在這邊想要說一點什麼
there is a gentleman over here please
請這邊有一位先生
right
對
my personal opinion
我個人的覺得
when China was in the present
是中國在當代的時候
Sanitary conditions will be inconvenient
衛生條件會長不方便
yes also bad
對 也很差
Yes, for example, a child poops on the bed
對 比如說小孩子有大便在床上
how to clean
怎麼去清洗
elder
老人
This dying old man or something
這個臨重的老人或是什麼老人
sick old man
得病的老人
What to do with the back row
後排要怎麼處理
I thought it was time to go far
我覺得當時的就是要走很遠
Right, the doorman outside Sijakun
對 西加坤外面的走門員
yes there is such a situation
是 有這種情況
Is it a matter of Ovarian?
是不是奧變的問題
Infected and mixed
感染了以及雜居
For example, we are in Minbei
比如說我們在民北那個地方
there is a play called what
有一個什麼叫做什麼劇
Such a large communal situation
這樣一個大的雜居這個狀況
So to make this contagion update the expansion
所以使這個感染力更新的擴大
Yes, as for not controlling me
對 至於沒有把我控制
yes thank you
是 謝謝
just him
就他這個
That's exactly what people at the time imagined.
當時的人的確就是這樣想像的
I think it's a
就覺得說是個
many people live together
很多人在雜居
And we live together very closely
而且大家在一起的生活又很密切
mix everything together
吃東西都混在一起
caused by
而造成的
At that time, such a situation was also described
當時也是描述這樣的一個狀況
ok then i am speaking
好 那我是的來講
just if it's not a coincidence
就是如果不是巧合的話
What might be the mechanism behind the difference
不如而同背後可能是什麼機制
I will give you a report
我跟大家做一個報告
In fact, a possible mechanism behind it is that
其實背後可能的一個機制就是說
in the west
在西方的
Three important health systems
三種重要的衛生體系
In fact, it simultaneously creates three
其實它同時伴隨創造出三個
a different identity
不同的一個身份
How should I put it? Let me talk about the first example.
怎麼說呢 我講第一個例子好了
The first example is quarantine
第一個例子是隔離檢疫
Everyone knows today, right?
就今天大家都知道對不對
It reinforces a sovereign state
它強化的是一個主權國家
Identity within a sovereign state
在一個主權國家之內的認同
because the threat we feel at this time
因為這時候我們感覺到的威脅
It's all from the outside, right?
其實都是來自外部對不對
from the port from outside
來自港口從外面來的
So you in order to prevent this disease
所以你為了防止這種病
Just like the FAKE we talked about before
就像我們以前講的FAKE
In fact, Quarantine is related to the Black Death, right?
其實Quarantine就是跟黑死病有關對不對
So you will put Jiang Jie in your country
所以你就會把你國家的江戒
Fortify it, don't let outsiders in
鞏固起來 不要外面的人進來
that in doing so
那在這樣做的過程中
In fact, you have to have the sovereignty of a sovereign country
其實你要有主權國家的主權
you control the port
你才能控制港口
But doing it will also let the people inside
可是做了同時也會讓裡面的人
stronger feeling says
更強烈的感覺到說
The threat is from outside
威脅是來自外面的
In fact, many times in the 19th century
那其實19世紀很多時候
Everyone names the disease
大家把病取名字
are named after another country.
都是取另外一個國家的名字
That is to say, the American drug is from another country.
就是說這個美毒是別的國家來的
right
對不對
So this health system of this quarantine
所以這種隔離檢疫的這個衛生體系
Its boundaries are equivalent to surrounding a
它的邊界就等於是圍繞著一個
space on the map
地圖上的空間
and make you inside
而使得你內
it requires you to be a sovereign state
它需要你有主權國家
To be able to implement such a health system
才能夠執行這樣的一個衛生體系
while executing
而在執行的
In the process of implementation, it will be further strengthened
實行的過程中又會進一步的強化
The people inside feel that we are a community of life
裡面的人感覺到我們是生命的共同體
Then we have common interests
然後我們有共同的利益
Then isolate yourself from outside threats.
然後跟外面的威脅要隔絕開
That's why something like
這也是為什麼像
Since the outbreak of COVID-19, many people will say
COVID-19發生以來很多人會說
Don't we claim to be entering a globalized world?
我們不是號稱進入全球化的世界嗎
Why all of a sudden
怎麼突然一下大家都把
The gates are closed
國門都關起來了
right
對不對
In fact, at the beginning, no one wanted to close the door.
其實一開始的時候誰都不願意關門
Because in fact, this method was rarely used by the nineteenth century.
因為其實這個方法到十九世紀就已經很少人採用了
because the adoption will lead to
因為採用就會導致
disruption of international trade
各國際貿易的中斷
interruption of communication
交流的中斷
But when the disease comes, you will be forced to take this approach
可是等到這個病來的時候你就會被迫採取這個做法
So in fact, COVID-19 is forcing us to adopt a
所以其實COVID-19就是逼我們採用一個
It hasn't been done for a long time
很久都沒有不採用的做法了
but at the same time it will
但做了同時就會
Let you feel a strong anti-globalization force
讓你感覺到一個強烈的一個反全球化的力量
consolidated a sovereign state
鞏固了一個主權國家的一個
self-identity
自我認同
I think that's what we've all experienced
這我想就是我們大家親身經歷的
a very large force
一個非常大的力量
And the second one is health science in the nineteenth century
那第二個呢是十九世紀的衛生科學
A boundary it reinforces is an anatomical body
它強化的一個邊界是個解剖學的身體
how to say everyone has heard
怎麼說大家都聽過
Chinese public health
中國公共衛生開始
It's John Snow, right?
就是John Snow嘛 對不對
He found a water
他發現有一個水
a water supply place
一個水 供水的地方
spreads mischief
是傳播禍亂的
So only World Health Sciences
所以只有世界衛生科學
One of his concerns
他的關注點的一個將戒
is my body
就是我的身體
relationship to my environment
跟我的環境間的關係
anything can get in my body
什麼都可以進到我身體
It's probably a cure, right?
很可能是治病的 對不對
such as water
比如說水
Or the air I breathe, etc.
或者說我呼吸的空氣等等
that is
就是
you will be very concerned about me this
你會非常關心我這個
so-called anatomy students
所謂解剖學生
it's my body
就是我這個肉體
around my whole skin
環繞著我整個皮膚
I will pay attention to all the holes
所有的孔穴我都會注意
Because that's where the disease comes in
因為病是從那裡進來的
Then other diseases also come out from the hole
然後另外病也是從孔穴出去的
So for example our pee and poop
所以說比如說我們的小便跟大便
suddenly became a big problem
就突然間變成一個大問題
It is Semitic Science
就是Semitic Science
Just to build a sewer
就是開小建立下水道
Because those things may make the disease
因為那些東西都可能會把病
bring to others
帶給其他人
So there is even a
所以甚至於還有一個就是說
our pores
我們的毛孔對不對
and suddenly we have for our
就突然間我們對於我們的
The sweat becomes a great concern, too
那個出汗也變成非常的關注
So the result of the development of this science
所以這個科學的發展的結果
makes us pay unprecedented attention to
就使得我們史無前例的注意
Our relationship with the environment
我們跟環境之間的關係
And pay attention to monitor
而且很注意來監視
The mouth of our body
我們身體的嘴巴啊
And that is to say
還有就是說那個
genitals, wait
生殖器啊等等
There are pores and so on
還有毛孔等等的孔道
So strengthened an anatomical body
所以強化了一個解剖學的身體
the other one is
那另外一個就是
When does the boundary between our body and the environment
那什麼時候我們這個身體跟環境的邊界
It's dangerous if you don't know
如果是不清楚的時候就覺得很危險
because you have to protect the border
因為你要保護這個邊界
what is one of those dangerous times
那其中一個危險的時候就是什麼
that's when I'm going back to the environment
就是我要回到環境的時候
when i die
就是我死掉的時候
So at that time, we will pay great attention to disposing of the dead body.
所以那時候也會很注意處理屍體
right
對不對
dead bodies suddenly become a big problem
屍體突然變成一個大問題
Then start the one around
然後開始各地的那個
The cemetery that was originally built in the city center
本來都建在市中心的那個墳場
All will be transferred to foreign affairs
全部都要移到交外去
It's like saying our excrement is suddenly down the drain
就像說我們的排泄物突然被進到下水道一樣
So the rise of this science
所以這個科學的興起呢
will strengthen our one is to say
會強化我們一個就是說
you feel this in your body
你感覺對你身體的這個
Note that a skin surrounds all the holes
一個皮膚環繞著所有的孔穴的注意
Then this is the health science of Xiyou Century
然後這是習友世紀的衛生科學
Then to personal hygiene in the first half of the second century
然後到二世紀上半夜的個人衛生
His focus is not on our relationship to our environment
他所注重的就不是我們跟環境間的關係
but the exchange of substances between the bodies
而是身體之間的物質交換
like we just saw this picture right?
就像我們剛剛看到這個圖對不對
Is the focus today on my relationship with the environment?
今天重點的是不是說我的跟環境
Rather, from certain fluids in another person's body
而是說從另外一個人身體裡的某些液體
run to my problem
跑到我的身上的問題
Kissing, for example, suddenly became a very dangerous act.
譬如說親吻突然間也變成一個很危險的行為了
In fact, at that time there was a Poster talking about
就其實那時候還有Poster講說
Kissing can be dangerous
Kissing can be dangerous
Then from this point of view, it means
然後在這個角度上來講就是說
Our hygiene keeps reminding you that
我們這個衛生就不斷的提醒你說
you have to be very careful
你要非常注意
When you exchange physical property with others
你跟別人有體業交換的時候
Whether we drink from the same cup, right?
無論是我們用同一個杯子喝水對不對
or eat
或者說吃飯
Or what kind of physical exchange
或者說還有哪一種體業交換
It's an STD, right?
就是性病對不對
when you find out about sex
你發現性關係的時候
You will also have a physical exchange
你也會有體業的交換
What about the rise of hygiene?
那這一個衛生的興起呢
would make us very aware
就會使我們非常注意到
material exchange between bodies
身體之間的物質交換
There is also the social distance between people and the world
還有人跟人間的社會距離
So this strengthens a concern between us and the human world
所以這是強化了一個我們人跟人間的一個關注
All of a sudden we're going to pay a lot of attention to this
突然間我們會非常注意這件事
So from this point of view
那所以從這角度來講
The story we just told today
我們剛剛今天講的這個故事
In fact, it is related to the personal hygiene in the middle of the night
其實是跟這個上半夜的個人衛生
And what happened is closely related
而發生的事情是密切相關的
Then I give these three examples to say
那我舉這三個的例子是說
I just said these two things
我剛剛說這兩個東西
What I just said is what I said earlier
剛剛我講就是跟前面我講說
Vice Miss' thoughts and Ge Chenghui's thoughts
副思念的想法跟葛誠會的想法
why close
為什麼會接近呢
It is because in fact, when the three health systems are in operation
就是因為其實這三個衛生體系在運作的時候
It will invisibly strengthen certain identities
它無形中都會強化某些身份認同
So its original concern
所以它本來關心的問題
it's about who we are
就會是跟我們是什麼樣的人有關的
so will be combined
因此會結合在一起
Then we go further with this
然後我們進一步來講這個
It can also be implemented when you are in epidemic prevention
也可以落實在一些你在防疫的時候
Remotely used or unused utensils
遙用或不用的器物有關
For example, didn't you just talk about that
譬如說剛剛不是講說那個
Isn't it very critical to take number two, right?
接二號不是很批評抗嗎對不對
anti-intermediate angle
抗中間的角度
Anti-period is a pretty good thing that saves energy
抗期是一個蠻好的很節省能源的東西
Because it is combined with the creation
因為它跟造是合在一起的
Then everyone crowded on the resistance
然後大家都擠在抗上
It is also the most efficient use of limited energy
這也是最有效的利用有限的能源
Just heat it up there after you finish cooking so that everyone can live
就你煮完飯就熱那邊讓大家可以住
But at this moment, he suddenly became an evil head of state.
可是在這個時候突然間就變成一個萬惡的元首
That is to say, it can spread the disease
就是說又可以傳播疾病
Yes, just to the left is spreading the disease.
對就剛剛在左邊就是傳播疾病
everyone together
大家在一起
But on the other hand
可是另外一方面方面呢
It's not good to look at it from the perspective of four years.
在複四年的角度來看抗也是不好的
which means to say
這就意味著說
you have no privacy in this home
你在這個家裡你完全沒有私密的空間
right
對不對
Every moment of your every second is seen by others
你的每一時每一刻每一秒都被別人所看到
you can't develop your personality
你沒有辦法培養你的個性
because you don't have a separate space
因為你沒有一個獨立的空間
So this resistance is equivalent to changing
所以這個抗就等於變
suddenly became a symbol
突然間變成一個象徵
It both infects germs and kills personalities
它既傳染病菌又惡殺個性
Especially at home plus this room
特別在家裡加上這個房間裡
I like to close the windows
又喜歡把窗戶關起來
It even said that it seems that your home is closed.
更表示說好像你這個家是封閉著
and you little kid in there
然後你這個小孩子在裡面
The one who was murdered developed this personality
被惡殺的一個發展這個個性
easy to get sick
又很容易得病
It is the pursuit of hygiene and the pursuit of individuality
就是追求衛生跟追求個性
both are suppressed
兩者都被壓抑
In addition, I showed you one
那另外呢我給大家看了一個
personal hygiene cup
就叫個人衛生杯
This is the health experiment station of Peking Union Medical College Hospital
這是北京協和醫院的衛生實驗站
A photo from 1935
1935年的一個照片
That means
那就是說
from now on is to say
現在開始就是說
we just didn't talk
我們剛剛不講
Don't experience the exchange, right?
不要體驗交換嘛對不對
so start
所以開始
Everyone Has Everyone's Own Cup
每個人有每個人自己的杯子
even numbered
甚至有編號
So when you want to use
所以你要用的時候
you use your own cup
你就用你自己的杯子
that in fact even in
那事實上甚至於在
It is also mentioned in the textbook
教科書裡的也有講
I use my own
我用我自己的
my own teacup
我自己的茶杯
Then your method is
那你這個方法就是
In this way you are reinforcing
這個方法你就是在強化說
You feel
你感覺
you have to realize
你要意識到
your contact with others
你跟別人的接觸
actually very dangerous
其實非常的危險
so you gotta have your own teacup
所以你要擁有你自己的茶杯
Then while you're using your own teacup
那在你用這個自己的茶杯的過程中
Actually you too
其實你也
Invisibly educating you
無形中在教育你
It's because you don't like to use it with others
就是你不喜歡跟別人用
when you use it with others
你跟別人用的時候
even nauseated
甚至產生噁心感
you guys need to know what i mean
大家要瞭解我的意思
From this point of view
從這角度上來講呢
One he can both defend personal hygiene
一個他可以既保衛個人的衛生
It also strengthens a sense of individualism and a body
又強化一種個人主義的一個身體感
It's just that you don't like sharing things with others.
就是你不喜歡跟別人分享東西
What about Feijie and Hygiene Habits?
那費捷和衛生習慣呢
Just like individualism is a kind of self-identity
就跟個人主義是一種自我認同
equal to the mutual support of the two
等於兩者相互支持
So we usually talk about individualism
所以我們平常講個人主義的話
is a value
是一種價值觀
Or a way to protect your personal
或者說是一種譬如說保障你的個人的
law of power
權力的法條
But in fact, it is also implemented in a body
可是其實也落實在一個身體上
you are like this
就是你是一個這樣子的
such a bodily sensation
這樣子的一種身體感受
you have to use your own teacup
你要用自己的茶杯
A condition that you don't want to mix with other people
你不願意跟別人混在一起用的一個狀況
good
好
So to say you see we can see now is to say
那所以說你看我們現在可以看到就是說
I just said why these two colluded
剛剛我說這兩個為什麼會合謀
Why all the Chinese families
為什麼都不約而同的把中國家庭
authority as a problem
視為問題的權員
serious personal harm
對個人帶來重大的傷害
that on these two utensils
那在這兩個器物上
Their position is the same
他們立場又是一致的
Both sides criticized the
雙方都抨擊抗
Then the use of personal hygiene cups will be encouraged, right?
然後都會鼓勵採用個人衛生杯對不對
so that's it
所以就這樣
Those two are walking together again
那雙方又是走在一起的
the worst the worst
那最嚴重最嚴重的
Reasons for Defejah's Problems
認為得費傑赫的問題的原因
In fact, it is a unique consensus system in China
其實是中國特有的共識制
when you eat
就是你吃東西的時候
Everyone confuses those chopsticks with whore roots
大家都把那個筷子跟嫖根
into the same soup, right?
到同一個湯裡對不對
It's like saying you're exchanging this
就等於說你在交換這個
while you exchange saliva
你交換口水的同時
pass germs to each other
把病菌傳給彼此
That's what they thought the disease was
就是他們當時認為這個病
the reason why it's so serious
會那麼嚴重的原因
so this is the biggest challenge
所以這是最大的挑戰
Then there is no way to solve a major problem
然後沒有辦法解決一個重大的問題
that is also at this time
那也是在這個時候
So Wu Liande is the one
所以五連德被就是那個
asked to come
被要求來
That is to say, to solve this problem
就是說要解決這個問題
Then the problem was
那這個問題在當時
How serious did people think it was?
當時的人覺得有多嚴重呢
You see, it's Kei Katsuragi who said again
你看就是葛城慧他又講
That is to say, facing this situation, he said
就是說面臨這個情況他說
He said that when you go to another house
他就講說當你去別這個家裡
when still adopting the Chinese way of eating
仍然採取中國式的吃東西的方法的時候
There's only one way you can defend yourself
你自衛的方法只有一個辦法
it's you sneaking first
就是你先偷偷
Hurry up and take out a scoop of each dish
趕快每個菜你弄一瓢出來
Then you don't eat it until someone else eats it
然後等到別人吃這個你就不吃了
That's a policy of self-defense of last resort.
那這是不得已的自衛政策
If you deal with it properly, you can only be a little faster than others
如果應付得當只有比別人快一點
others may not see
別人可能看不出來
It was you who secretly ate first
就是你自己偷偷的先吃了
so you can feel in this
所以你可以感覺到在這個
as far as he is concerned
就以他個人來講
how much he believes
他多麼的相信
The disease brought about by this consensus
這個這種共識之所帶來的疾病
is he would mind such a solution
是他會介意這樣的解決方法
that this
那這
yes you can watch
是你就可以看
You can see where he is absolutely in danger.
就可以看出這個他絕對的危險所在
good
好
then in this case
那就在這個情況下
equal to why we just said
等於我們剛剛為什麼說
Wuliande will come to create this
五連德會要來創造這個
It is because he is facing such a predicament
就是因為他面對的是這樣的一個困局
that is
就是說
every day when everyone is eating
每天每個人在吃東西的時候
equal to one of the most important
等於就是一個最重要的一個
Ways and channels of infection
傳染的途徑和管道
right
對不對
how to solve this
那這要怎麼來解決
So he came up with three possibilities
所以他就想出三種可能性
What about the first possibility?
那第一種可能性呢就是說
take-out tense
就採取分時制
just like westerners
就跟西方人一樣
then you are going
那你就是走向
like a personal hygiene cup, right?
像個人衛生杯對不對
Divide the dishes first, everyone eats everyone's
菜先分好每個人吃每個人的
so we don't exchange
這樣我們就不會交換
Exchanging that drool won't spread the germs either.
交換那個口水也不會傳播病菌了
what did he say
那可他說呢
He doesn't think it's a good way to eat Chinese food
他覺得這不是一個吃中式餐點的好方法
He is Malaysian Chinese
那他是馬來西亞華人喔
that is so you see
就是說所以你看
he makes the decision now
他現在做這個決定
On the one hand, it is a matter of hygiene
一方面是衛生的問題
On the one hand, it will have a profound impact on
一方面會深遠的影響
the way we eat in the future, right?
以我們以後用餐的方式對不對
It even means that the relationship between us and others
乃至於就是說我們人跟人間的關係
He said it's not a good way
他說這不是好方法
but he didn't make it clear
但他沒有講得很清楚
Why does he think it's not a good way
為什麼他覺得不是好方法
Instead, I was in a 1950
後來我反而在1950年的一個
The doctor in Taiwan wrote that
台灣的那個醫生的他有寫說
Why does he think this is not a good way
他為什麼覺得這不是好方法
He said you have to eat whole fish because of Chinese food
他說因為中式的菜你都要吃完整的魚
whole chicken whole duck
完整的雞完整的鴨
It's like dividing the rotten mess on everyone's plate
等於把弄得爛爛的分到每個人盤子裡的時候
not good
就不好吃了
So he thinks it's not a good way
所以他覺得這不是一個好方法
so this is actually quite interesting
所以這其實蠻有趣的
I quite agree with him
像我也蠻同意他的意見
It's a good thing we didn't adopt this food sharing system
就還好我們沒有採取這個分食制
For more than five years, I said that this is not a good way.
那五年多就說這不是好方法
What about the second one? He strengthened it.
那第二個呢他強化就是說
Everyone should have two pairs of chopsticks
每個人都要有兩雙筷子
So you just have a pair of chopsticks
所以你就一雙筷子呢
For example, you say that I am catching that fish now.
你就譬如說我現在接那個魚
You pick up that fish with a chopstick
你用一個筷子去接那個魚
put it in
放到放進來之後
You change another chopstick
你再換另外一個筷子
come in your mouth
來接到你的嘴巴裡
Then he said another pair of chopsticks
然後他說另外一雙筷子呢
you should use red
你應該要用紅色的
That's like a reminder that it's dangerous
這樣就等於提醒說這是有危險的
just use it on yourself
就是只能用在你自己的身上
But he said it's not a good way
可是他說這也不是好方法
In fact, it is said that I was the one just now
其實據說剛我就是剛那位那個
The guest mentioned Song Meiling
來賓提到講宋美玲
It is said that Song Meiling's family used these two pairs of chopsticks
據說講宋美玲家就是用這兩雙筷子的方法
It's not a good way to say it in five years
那五年得就說這也不是好方法
Because of his own trial results
因為他自己試用的結果
I found it very easy to get confused
我發現非常容易就弄混了
It's the slowness, you can't figure it out
就是這個過緩你就搞不清楚
Which pair is which pair of chopsticks
哪一雙是哪一雙的筷子
That is in this context
那就是在這樣的脈絡下
He finally said he designed this
他最後才說他設計這個
Hydrogenic Chinese Dining Table
Hydrogenic Chinese Dining Table
invent this
發明這個
In fact, this is to cooperate with the male and female pools
那其實這個就是要配合公塊母池
It has a detailed description of how the plate is to be made
它有仔細地描述這個盤子要怎麼製作
so it really thinks it invented it
所以它真的認為這是它發明的
Then the key point is that it should be combined with the male block and the female pool
然後重點就是它要加上公塊母池配合在一起
So what is the purpose of this plate?
那所以這個盤子的目的什麼就是說
because if you don't have this plate
因為如果你沒有這個盤子的話
For dishes farther away, you can’t get the male and female pools, right?
遠一點的菜你拿不到那個公塊母池嘛 對不對
If you have this plate, you can put it
那你有這個盤子的話你可以把它
Turn in front of you and follow the male and female pool
轉到你面前然後隨著公塊母池過來
you can use
你就可以使用
So in a situation like this
所以在這樣的情況下
it thinks it designed this
它覺得它設計出了這個
Solved a hygiene problem
解決了一個衛生的問題
And at the same time it can
而同時呢它又可以
Solved the problem of sanitation
解決了衛生的問題
But it's not fully remodeled
可是它又沒有完全改造
innate way of eating
固有的吃東西的方式
the relationship between me and a person
和一個人我之間的關係
So it's very proud to think it's a
所以它非常驕傲覺得這是一個
combined with a traditional way of dining
結合了一個傳統用餐方式
and an indigenous innovation of modern hygiene principles
和現代衛生原則的一個本土創新
so in other words
所以換句話說
Even when you face this hygiene challenge
即便你面臨到這個衛生的挑戰時候
You can still create a way
你仍然可以創造出一個方式
To protect some original social relations
來保護某些原來的社會關係
you eat full chinese food
你吃完整的中餐
Then it means that everyone hangs out and eats together.
然後就是說大家在一起混的吃的關係
In fact, we put this matter
那其實這個事情我們放在
The cultural history of 1924 is actually a
1924年的文化史裡其實是一個
You may feel small now
大家現在可能覺得很小
But it was a big deal at the time
可是其實在當時是一個大事
Because it affects people's social relations
因為就影響到人的社會關係
For example, let me show you a picture
譬如說我給大家看一個圖
This picture is a round table in Japan on Tatami
這個圖就是塔塔米上的日本有的一個圓桌
right
對不對
you may want to
大家可能很想
It's also a modern invention
這也是現代的發明
When the Japanese eat at the table
就日本人本來在桌上吃的時候
each eats his own
是各吃各的
Then came the introduction of Western civilization
後來就是引入西方文明的時候
they get a concept
他們得到一個概念
That is to say the definition of a Happy Family
就是說一個Happy Family的定義
Just want everyone to eat together
就是要大家圍在一起吃飯
no such words
沒有這樣子的話
no real family feeling
就沒有一個真正的家庭的感受
That's why I invented this table
所以才發明了這樣的一個桌子
So the story I just told is that
那所以我剛剛講的這個故事就是說
Actually our
其實我們的
Various difficulties encountered in order to prevent the epidemic
為了防疫所遇到的種種的困難
Artifacts created by concepts
概念所創造出來的器物
and that bodily sensation
和那個身體感受
have profoundly affected us
都深遠的影響了我們
that's a
那這是一個
So we may often
所以我們可能很多時候
didn't realize
就沒有意識到
But as long as we think about today, if we
但是只要是想今天我們如果
no longer eating on that plate
不再是在那個盤子裡吃
But if everyone gets a share
而是每人分成一份的話
Our lives may really have changed a lot
我們的生活可能真的發生了很大的改變
That's what I'm going to report to you today.
那這就是我今天跟大家報告的主題
thank you all
謝謝大家
Thank you so much Mr. Ray
這個非常謝謝雷所長
give a very good speech
帶來非常精采的演講
I believe that everyone has gained as much as I have.
我相信大家跟我一樣都收穫滿滿了
then we were
那我們本來是
The top ten guests who asked questions
這個前十名發提問的這個現場來賓
we have prepared a beautiful little gift
我們有準備一個精美的小禮物
That's because a few friends have already asked questions
那因為剛才已經有幾位朋友已經提問了
Then we are open Q&A now
那我們一樣現在就是開放Q&A
And as long as it's the top ten
然後只要是前十位呢
We have this in our homestay
我們這個民宿處有這個
Speaking of we are two or three questions your answer
說到我們是兩三位提問您的回答
It's all good, okay, okay
都好可以可以可以
Okay two or three
好兩三位好了
good good good
好好好
Like this, please answer again
這樣子你再請回答
Are we the first
那我們是不是第一個
In the first round we collect two or three questions
第一回合我們就先收集個兩三個問題
Professor Lei, have you ever visited South Korea
雷教授您曾經在韓國訪問過
Then the Koreans eat
那麼韓國人他們吃飯
How are their habits different from those of the Chinese?
他們的習慣跟中國人有什麼不太一樣的地方
Or is it different from how Taiwanese eat?
或是跟台灣人吃飯的情況有什麼不太一樣
Recently, the epidemic in South Korea has been soaring
最近在韓國的這個疫情一直往上飆
terrible
太可怕了
Thanks
謝謝
ok thanks for coming
好 謝謝 來
Hello Professor Lei
雷教授您好
I find it very interesting the way you use that inference
我覺得非常有意思您用那個推論的方式
Then discuss which family becomes a most bonded one
然後討論那個家庭變成是一個最結合的一個病緣
Then there is a conclusion that the transformation of the traditional Chinese family is a process before pathology
然後有一個結論是傳統中國家庭變成是一個病理化之前的過程
If we take an inference like yours
如果我們把您這樣的一個推論方式
And compared to what the West is talking about
並比於西方在談這個這個
Abandoned festivals are a disease of civilization caused by modernization
廢節合是一個文明病現代化的一個造成的
So is it under such a history in the West?
那麼是不是在西方的這樣的一個歷史下面
There is also such a thing as industrialization and urbanization
也有出現這樣的就是把那個工業化都市化
The condition of a phenomenal society that also pathologizes it
也把它病理化的一個現象社會的狀況
or there is such a discourse produced
或是有這樣的論述產生
because what we see seems to be an opposite result
因為我們看到的好像是一個相反的結果
It is they who want to promote the economy instead
是他們反而要去促進經濟
Then caused a second wave of accelerated industrialization
然後造成了第二波的加速的工業化
yes
是
Thanks
謝謝
that there was no socialist country
那沒有一個社會主義的國家的產生
So rise up at that time
所以在那個時候興起
yes
是
Thanks
謝謝
ok maybe one more question
好 也許可以再一個問題
Let's ask Lei Shao to answer together
我們再請雷少一起回答
come please
來 請
It is because of this economic factor that the dissemination of scrap joints
是因為這個經濟因素而導致廢節合的傳播
Is it possible that
那有沒有可能是因為
The Great Depression of 1929
1929年的經濟大蕭條
And that leads to saying that people start to have this kind of thinking
而導致說人們開始有這樣的思考
However, it was discovered that China
但是又發現中國因為
was not affected by the events of 1929
並沒有受到1929事件的影響
think about family
而往家庭方面去思考
To infer that China's puzzling box came from the family
去推說中國的費解盒是從家庭出來
rather than economically
而不是從經濟層面
thanks for your questions
謝謝大家的問題
In terms of this last question
就這種最後一個問題來講
In fact, it is considered to be a social problem.
其實認為是一個社會問題的這件事情
You see what I mentioned in the title of the book just now
你看我剛剛的書名提到
19th century France
19th century France
It actually happened at the end of the 19th century
就是其實在19世紀末就已經發生了
So in fact, everyone knows that at the end of the 19th century
那所以其實大家知道19世紀末期
a lot of socialist ideas
就是很多社會主義的思潮
It's all started, right?
都已經開始興起了對不對
I think it's social structure
覺得就是社會結構上
In fact, it is very harmful to human health
其實對人的健康造成很大的傷害
So in fact, it should not need to go to 1929
所以其實應該是不需要到1929年的
The Great Depression Happened
經濟大蕭條才發生
Already happened at the end of the 19th century
就19世紀末已經發生了
Probably such a situation
大概是這樣子的一個狀況
The question you asked just now is a very good question
那剛剛那位您問的問題是個很好的問題
Indeed
的確是
that is
就是說
So what we mean by civilization disease is actually very contradictory.
所以我們講文明病的意思其實就很矛盾
Because civilization is inherently good, right?
因為文明本來是好的對不對
But I feel that civilization may bring disease
可是卻又覺得文明可能會帶來疾病
So in fact, from this point of view, it means
那所以其實在這個角度來講就是說
As we just said, for example
像我們剛剛講的就是譬如說
The establishment of the 8-hour working hour system per day, etc.
每日8小時的工時制的建立等等
equal to this question
等於對於這個問題
The problems brought about by the civilization of media
media這個文明所帶來的問題
Indeed some people regard it as a
的確有人把它當成是一個
just this article
就這個文
as a text
是當成一個文
critique of civilization
對文明的批判
you are right
您講的沒有錯
Another well-known response to the so-called disease of civilization is
另外很有名的對所謂文明病就是
neurasthenia
神經衰弱
Of course, these were probably the two most famous diseases at the time.
那當然這可能是當時最有名的兩個病
that is to say, people would think
就是說會人們認為
Actually you should be able to trace back to our civilization
其實你應該可以追溯到我們的文明
brought about by a negative place
所帶來的一個負面的地方
so you are right
所以您講的是對的
Then you just talked about a situation in South Korea
然後剛剛您講韓國的一個情形
Actually, I dare not say that I understand so well
其實我不敢說那麼了解
the state of their meals
他們用餐的狀況
Then
然後
You start by telling me that I can't remember
您先講我一直回憶不起來
I can only
我只能
I probably remember my first time
我可能記得有我第一次吧
I just got this research result
我剛剛這個研究結果
When sharing with a Korean medical historian
跟一個韓國醫學史家分享的時候
He said why the Koreans didn't invent this thing
他說怎麼韓國人沒有發明這個東西
So he probably felt there was some kind of relationship
所以他可能覺得有一些類似的關係
But I don't know that much about Korea
但我對韓國沒有了解到那麼多
to answer this question
來回答這個問題
Excuse me
不好意思
I would like to ask this is the part about this study
我想請問一下這是關於這個研究的部分
Is there any data found later?
有沒有就是後面有找到一些數據
Said that after using this stall
說使用這個攤盤之後
Some reduction related data of FJH
費捷合的一些減少的相關的數據
Are there statistics?
統計數據有嗎
or is this a
還是就是這是一個
One of our conclusions from the previous
我們從前面結論得到的一個
A food that can still be seen
現在還看得到的一個食品
But maybe when collecting data
但是可能在蒐集數據的時候
not that much research
沒有那麼多的研究
I don't believe there is such a Fei Jiehe
不信有沒有這個費捷合
This data actually reduces
實際減少的這個數據
Is there this connection
有沒有這個關聯性
Okay, thank you
好謝謝
any left
還有沒有
come here sir
來 這邊先生
Huang Peiren
黃沛忍
Huang Peiren ask the teacher for advice
黃沛忍請教一下老師
that now a group meal
那個現在的一個團餐
Fuji-Canada Group
大集團像富士堪大集團
Everyone said big dinner
大家說大餐嘛
it's a big meal
是大餐就是
it's a buffet style
它是一種自助餐式的
such a
這樣的一個
wrong work
失誤的工作
Will it change later
是不是會改變以後
this whole one
這種整個一個
one of the dining habits
用餐習慣的一個
Way
方式
even brought home
甚至帶到家裡來
I bring it home like this
我帶到家裡來這樣
Thanks
謝謝
any left
還有沒有
we can three questions
我們可以三個問題
Then please this
然後一併請這個
Director Lei, Mr. Lei
雷所長雷老師
Listen to our answer Line
聽我們回答Line
I'm Hou
我是侯
idea is to say
想法就是說
During the teacher's speech just now, you can see
老師剛剛演講的過程中可以看到
That is to say, the relationship between people and diseases is from
就是說人們跟疾病之間的關係是從
national power
國家力量
start to get deeper into the individual
開始逐漸深入到個人之上
and remove people from the family
然後把人從家庭中
Freed from traditional family
從傳統家庭解放出來
and then controlled by state power
然後由國家力量去控制
Did he also affect the later 49 years later
他是不是也影響到後來就是49年之後
Chinese Communist Party in
中國共產黨在
Some views on medical care in this process in China
中國這個過程中的一些對於醫療的看法
How will it change that's my first question
會是怎樣的變化這是我第一個問題
The second question I look at from the context of European history
第二個問題我比較從歐洲史的脈絡來看
words mean
的話就是說
From the cross tank written by that country autumn in the past
從以前那個國家秋寫的十字坦
to the one written by fukuguchi
再到像福口所寫的那本
The history of madness books have about the so-called wind power guys
瘋狂史的書本裡面有關於那些所謂風電之人
like being locked in bed
在被關在床上面一樣
Plus it's like
再加上就是像是
Thomas Mann in his
Thomas Mann在他的那個
Zauberberg's novel also describes
Zauberberg那本小說裡面也描寫到說
Fei Jiehe's patients
費捷和的患者
They are usually a rich bourgeois
他們通常都是一個有錢的資產階級
locked in a
被關在了一個
A very luxurious mountain on a Swiss mountain
一個瑞士的山上一個非常的豪華的山上裡面的
such a process
這樣子的過程
Then I don't know what the teacher thinks about it
那我不知道老師怎麼去看待
Such a change or how to be honest about such a phenomenon
這樣子的變化或是怎麼樣去誠實這樣子的現象
Thanks
謝謝
Yes Yes
是是
that
那個
Thank you for your question
謝謝大家剛剛的問題
First
第一
the first question you asked me
第一位您問我的問題
to be honest
坦白講
i didn't see
我是沒有看到
I don't see relevant research statistics
我沒有看到相關的研究統計的數據
And in fact Mandroid
而且其實Mandroid
in this story
就是這個故事中
In fact, this should follow
其實這樣應該是要跟著
The male and female pool
那個公塊母池
right
對不對
But I actually don't know the male pool and the female pool
可是我其實並不知道公塊母池
How popular was it at the time
在當時就已經流行到什麼程度
and frankly
而且坦白說
I
我
The first picture I just showed you
我剛剛給大家看的第一張圖
In fact, in 1965 in that China Town in the United States
其實1965年在那個美國的China Town
that is
就是說
now likely
現在很可能
Five years did invent the dinner plate in 1915
五年得的確在1915年就發明了這個餐盤
but it didn't really catch on
但是並沒有真正流行起來
when it became popular
流行起來的時候
In fact it is the result of restaurants adopting
事實上是餐館採用的結果
Well I now know that one was developed in Japan in 1930
那我現在知道一個是日本在1930的發展
another one is this
另外一個是這個
This is thought to have become popular later in China Town
這個是認為說是在China Town後來流行起來的
So in fact, when it became popular later, it didn’t follow
那所以其實後來流行的時候並沒有跟
Follow the male and female pool
跟著公塊母池
So that impact may be more limited
所以那影響就可能更有限了
So this your question is
所以這個您的問題就是
It's a very good and scientific question
是個很好的很科學的問題
Unfortunately we didn't
可惜我們後來並沒有
There is no way to trace this development
沒有辦法追溯這個發展
and then just another
然後剛剛另外
Is it the group meal you mentioned?
您講的團打餐的問題是不是
Actually that's an interesting question
其實這是很有趣的問題
that is
就是說
But now I also have a moment
可是我現在也一時間
don't know how to answer
不知道該怎麼回答
Just saying the things we can tell is that
只是說我們可以看得出來的事情就是說
I think this is one of my speeches today
我想這也是今天我演講的一個
pretty big spindle
蠻大的主軸
That is to say, after the germ theory became popular
就是說當細菌學說開始流行之後
It's actually very powerful
它的力量其實非常的大
that is, we might think
就是說我們可能以為
It's just a way to control the disease
它只是一個控制疾病的方式
But it actually got into our lives
可是它其實陷入了我們生活中
very detailed design
非常多的細節的設計
For example, like all the food we buy now
譬如說像我們現在買的所有食物
Almost all have plastic packaging, right?
幾乎都有塑膠包裝對不對
basically you don't trust any
就基本上你不信任任何
food without packaging
沒有包裝情況下的食物
because you feel the potential to contaminate
因為你都覺得潛在可能會污染
This is also the situation after the germ theory became popular.
那這也是細菌學說流行之後的狀況
But I want to eat in a group situation
可是我想在一個集體中用餐的情形
In fact, for example, whether in the army or in a factory
其實那個譬如說無論在軍隊或者說工廠裡
That must have an interesting history worth studying
那一定有一個很有趣的歷史值得研究
Then I can't do anything right now
那我現在一時間沒有辦法
don't know that much
沒有那麼了解
so no way to answer your good question
所以沒辦法回答您的好的問題
add more teacher
再補充一下老師
That is to say, in ancient times, a fair or a meeting of property officials
就是說在古代的一個公平或物官大會的一個
change collective
變革集體
right
對
It's also a big bunch
它也是一個很大的一個團團
That ancient group of bamboo flowers one by one
那個古代的這個團團的一個一個竹華
or sub-station
或是分站的做法
will it be
會不會是
In ancient times, there were many infectious diseases
那個古代的時候傳染病很多
yes
是
would cause a big one
會引起很大的一個
An explosion of contagion
爆大式的一個傳染
right
對
Also such an important one
也是這樣一個重要的一個
yes
是
a stunned look
一個昏襲來看
Not possible to be
不可能是
But that's the point of today's story
可是這就是今天這個故事的一個重點
that's when you won't doubt
就那個時候你不會懷疑
passed on to you by people close to you
是你身邊的人傳給你的
But now you're highly skeptical
可是現在的時候你會高度的懷疑
people around you pass it on to you
你身邊的人傳給你
You may even suspect that your family passed it on to you
甚至你會懷疑是你的家人傳給你的
So much so that it changed one of you and your family
所以以至於就改變了你跟你家人的一個
Look at the trust relationship of the people around you
看身邊人的一個信賴關係
Probably so. For intimacy.
大概是這樣 對親密關係是這樣子
hello then
然後您好
Your question first is very good
您的問題第一個是非常好
In fact, it was later in 1949
其實後來要1949就
The Communist Party of China says
中國共產黨就說
Fei Jie and is a society
費傑和是一個社會
And he said before
而且他就講說以前
The former capitalist Kuomintang
以前那個資本主義的國民黨
don't care about everyone
就不關心大家
So you never really have to fix the problem
所以你都從來沒有真正要解決這個問題
So the way they did it later was in the factory
所以他們後來做的方法就是在工廠裡
to build that
要建立那個
that
那個
equal to field one
等於場一
Then come to help with this problem
然後來幫忙解決這個問題
So this is later
所以這個是後來
That is, the Communist Party of China very much believes that
就是中國共產黨非常認為
They are different from the KMT's approach
他們不同於國民黨的一個做法
They are very highly publicized
他們又非常高度在宣傳
This is the side of Social Disease
就是Social Disease這一面
That is the only continuation of the period of the Kuomintang
那跟國民黨時期唯一延續
is for
就是對於
Dealing with the problem of spitting
吐痰這個問題的處理
So it turned out to be a major vice
就這原來被當一個重大的惡習
But that's another story
但這是另外一個story了
But they do put a lot of emphasis on
可是他們的確是非常高度強調
This is a social disease
這是一個social disease
in a capitalist society
而認為是資本主義社會中
unwilling to admit this social disease
不願意承認這個social disease
because you don't want to improve
因為你不願意改善
That is to say, a living environment for workers
就是說工人的一個生活環境
Probably such a situation
大概是這樣子的一個狀況
And then you later Thomsman's argument
然後你後來Thomsman的那個論點
I didn't understand that question very well
那個問題我沒有聽得很懂
can you explain more
你可以再多說明一下
I didn't understand the second part very well
第二個部分我沒有聽得很懂
The second part I want to ask is to say
第二個部分我想問的是說
The old four don't treat that European member
老四個不按待那個歐洲的會員
disease management point
病的管理點
yes
是
Because in these novels, for example, Stan
因為這些小說裡面比如說斯坦
Or like in that Fuko's book
或者像是在那個福扣的書本裡面
Or like in Thomasman's novel
或者像是Thomasman的那一本小說裡面
I thought of some phenomena about Fei Jiehe
想到了一些對於費捷和的一些現象
if go to control
如果去管控
How will he treat his phenomenon
他會如何去治療他這種現象
I don't know how the teacher treats this problem
不知道老師怎麼去看待這個東西的問題
yes
是
Fei Jiehe is sure you have heard of it
費捷和就是肯定你有聽說過
Is there a Chinese art book?
有一本有中藝本嗎
It was written by Su Zhenchang Pagoda
就是那個蘇貞昌塔寫的
Unice as the metaphor, right?
Unice as the metaphor對不對
That is Fei Jiehe is a special one, that is to say
就是費捷和是特別一個就是說
There are many descriptions in the literature
文學中有非常多人描述
because it is a chronic disease
因為就是慢性病
That is to say, and you can live a long time with this
就是說而且得了這還可以活很久
Then each has a lot of descriptions
然後每個人都有很多的描述
And once romanticized by that
而且一度是被那個 romanticize
right
對不對
So the childbirth thing I just talked about
所以剛剛講的那個臨代育的事
It's not just China
其實也不是只有中國這樣子
Even in the West there are such descriptions
就在西方也有這樣的描述
That is, after the people who can talk about Feigehe
就是說得了費傑河的人之後
That is to say, even women's faces will turn red
就是說連女性反而臉會泛紅
Yes, then there is a stronger
對 然後就是說有更強
more delicate sensibility
更纖細的感性
and love of life
以及對生命的熱愛
Then there are many love stories
然後就是描述很多愛情的故事
Then this one originally had such an image
那這個本來是有這樣一個形象的
So it's actually quite a positive image.
所以其實是蠻正面的形象
But so it's also about theater theory
可是所以這也是跟戲劇學說有關
After the theatrical theory came
等戲劇學說來了之後
when you see him you see a
你看到他的時候就會看到一個
very different him
很不同的他
just because you thought
就因為你本來認為
Because when the heroine was in the lungs
因為本來連女傑肺傑河的時候
In fact, when you are not contagious concepts
其實你沒有在傳染概念的時候
you might think it's a
你可能認為這是一個
a disease within him, right?
他內在的一個疾病對不對
so you might even think
所以你甚至會認為
While he sells his body
在他肉體銷售的同時
His inspiration even goes so far as to say
他的靈感甚至於說
The sensibility is enhanced
那個感受性都提升
love life more
更熱愛生命之類的
But when you see him later
可是等到後來你看到他的
when it becomes a sick head
就變成一個疾病人頭的時候
It's not easy to romanticize anymore
就不太容易再romanticize下去
So you see, it turns into saying
所以你看後來轉成說
that you are related to the poor
那個你跟窮人有關
This is also a very important point, right?
這也是個很重要的一點對不對
It's that part that transforms
就是那個部分就轉化了
Well, it's actually quite a complicated process.
那這其實是個蠻複雜的過程
Because this disease is very long
因為這個病很漫長
So there are a lot of people with a lot of related descriptions
所以有很多人有很多的相關的描述
The simplest thing to say is to say
那最簡單的講的話就是說
At one point he experienced a
一度他曾經經歷過一個
A process of being romanticized
一個被romanticize的過程
later became considered a poor man's disease
後來變成認為是一個窮人的疾病
even a social issue
甚至是一個社會問題
roughly like this
大致是這樣
right
對
Thank you Mr. Lei
謝謝雷老師
any left
還有沒有
we still have a little time
我們還有一點時間
opportunity for him to come
機會讓他來
Feel sorry
抱歉
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
謝謝老師的精采的演講
I'm bope from the law firm
我是法律所的博佩
Then I have a question is
那我有一個問題是
The teacher just had a powerpoint
老師剛剛有一張powerpoint
There are three identities mentioned
裡面有提到三個身份認同
Does the teacher want to explain through these three identities
那老師是不是想要透過這三個身分認同去解釋說
Why is the epidemic prevention from a scientific point of view
為何一方面從科學的角度的防疫
That's another aspect of individualism
那已經另外一方面個人主義
That leads to not asking children to criticize the concept of family
那都導致不約兒童去批判家庭這個概念
The first of these, identity, is national sovereignty.
那其中的第一個認同 身分認同是國家主權
I remember correctly, I was thinking
我沒記錯 那我在思考說
What about national sovereignty because it sounds like a
那國家主權怎麼跟 因為聽起來它就是一個
totalitarian concept of a society
極權一個社會的概念
how could cause
怎麼會導致會
It can be explained that behind the promotion of individualism
可以解釋說背後促進個人主義
Identity
身分認同
yeah sorry i miss me
對 不好意思 我想我
It's just that what I just said was not very clear
就是我剛剛講的沒有很清楚
In fact, it was just that
其實就是剛剛那個
What I said on that slide is actually
我在那個slide講的其實是說
We follow the prevention and control of this infectious disease
我們跟這個傳染病的防治
I just introduced three different systems, right?
我剛剛介紹就有三種不同的系統 對不對
that each different system
那每一個不同的系統
Makes you pay different attention to dangerous boundaries
使你對於危險的邊界產生不同的關注
that this focus on borders
那這個對邊界的關注
promotes a certain identity
就促成了某一種特定的認同
When isolation is easy
隔離簡易的時候
That border is not on the skin
那個邊界就不在皮膚
right
對不對
Not between people and the environment
不在人跟環境之間
not between people
也不在人跟人之間
This is the second and third
這是第二種第三種
The first one is spatial
那第一種都是空間性的
right
對不對
What about the spatial result?
那這個空間性的結果呢
that is
就是說
So in fact, what is strengthened is
所以其實強化的是
I am your person in this space
我這個空間你的人
with that space of your human world
跟那個空間你的人間的
different different
不同的不同
and i'm going to separate from you
而且我要跟你隔開
And I think the danger comes from there
而且我覺得危險來自於那邊
So it's not an individualistic identification
所以不是個人主義式的認同
but a collective identity
而是一個集體的認同
like
就譬如像
Actually I think like
其實我想就譬如像
Taiwan right?
台灣對不對
right now you feel like saying
就現在你會覺得說
we are
我們是
We have put the whole world
我們前陣子已經把全世界
Everywhere is considered a dangerous place
所有地方都當成危險的地方了
only we are safe
只有我們是安全的地方
right
對不對
The reason why this can be successful
那這個可以成功的原因
with us as a sovereign state
跟我們是主權國家
manageable borders
可以控管邊界有關
right
對不對
And at the same time, it will make you feel more strongly
而且同時也會更讓你強烈的感覺到說
The things around you are originally yours
你身邊的這些本來你的
for example
譬如說
We really wanted to support Hong Kong
我們本來很想支援香港
But now you can't help but see it as
可是現在你不能不把它看成
a dangerous source
一個危險的來源
it's just outside your homeland
它就是在你的國土之外
You are isolated from it
你跟它就是有隔絕的關係
This is also imperceptibly
這也無形中被
It is a common interest of the people within this regime who can exercise sovereign control
就是這個能夠施展主權控制的這個regime之內的人的一個共同的利益
right
對不對
You have common interests and your common security is protected
你們有共同利益你們共同安全被保護
People who are all within this line are united
都在這個線上之內的人被團結在一起
so it's really not personal
所以這的確不是個人的
but a situation within a sovereign state
而是一個主權國家的之內的一個情形
Then the question you mentioned is actually
那您講的問題其實
That is also a main axis that I want to share with you today.
也就是也是我今天想跟大家分享的一個主軸
that is
就是說
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講
We would have thought of this as a completely neutral treatment of disease.
我們本來覺得完全中性處理疾病的這個
these sanitation systems
這些衛生的體系
It will invisibly strengthen certain boundaries
它無形中一定會強化某些邊界
and then make us even develop certain habits
然後促成我們甚至養成某些習慣
then make our impact on us
然後使得我們對我們的影響
In fact, it is far more than a temporary control of a disease.
其實遠超過一時的一個控制一個疾病而已
a far-reaching impact of
的一個深遠的影響
probably like this
大概是這樣子
Thanks
謝謝
any left
還有沒有
Come
來
the professor i want to ask a question
那個教授我想請問一個問題
just now
就是剛剛
When someone asked a question just now, it was mentioned that
剛剛有人提問的時候提到說
It is after World War II if the treatment fee is resolved.
就是治療費解核的話是在二戰後
Just after the card is drawn out
就是等卡件描出來之後
what i want to ask is
我想問的是
just before the card is traced
就是在卡件描出來之前
The treatment of health experts in the event is to only put those
事件上衛生專家的治療方法是只有把那些
It's like improving ventilation or poor light production.
就是像是改善通風或是產光不良的一些問題
or the home quarantine you just mentioned
或是你剛剛提到的居家隔離
As far as those methods are concerned, my own thoughts are
就那些方法我自己的想法是說
only to slow down the rate of infection
就只能減緩傳染的速度
for those already infected
針對那些已經感染的人
Health experts at the time were
當時的衛生專家是
what method to take
有採取什麼樣的方法去
let them just
讓他們就
is healed or
痊癒嗎或是
what kind of therapy
什麼療法之類的
people who are already infected
就更能已經感染的人
In fact, it can only be sent to a nursing home.
其實就只能送到療養院
can do very limited
能做的事很有限的
From our perspective today, it is impossible to cure
就從我們今天角度來講是不可能治癒的
right
對不對
Just let him fix the itch
就只能讓他去修癢而已
And then there's the sun
然後還有曬太陽
then what else
然後還有什麼
Anyway, from our perspective today, it’s like what you said
反正從我們今天角度來講就像你說的
None of them are effective treatments
全部都不是有效的治療方法
just heal
只是使他療
it's a treat
是個療養樂
yes that's the case
對是這樣的情形
yes
是
we eat
我們吃
Not all Japanese dishes are like this
日本菜的時候不是都有這樣的
dinner plate
的餐盤
everyone eats their own
大家都是吃自己的
Then when eating Chinese food, everyone will not be together
然後吃中國菜的時候大家是不會在一起的
even that
就算是那個
that has that
那個有那個
rotating
旋轉的
Everyone at the dining table is still
的餐桌大家還是
Can eating this together reflect that
一起吃的這個是不是可以反映說
Japanese watermelon layers
日本的西瓜層層度受
Influence of Freedom of Thought
自由思潮的影響程度
than China
比中國
come deep
來的深
or
或者是說
China
中國
Even if China
中國就算
With the emergence of this revolving dining table
有這個旋轉餐桌的出現
Did it mean that liberalism was under the impact of the main ideas?
是不是以前是說自由主義在跟主家思想衝擊之下
did not completely change the thinking of the Chinese people
沒有完全的改變中國人的思想
That is to say, our Chinese-style dining table has its own bowls and plates
就是說我們的我們中式的餐桌一樣有自己的碗盤
But there is still a public wooden spoon
可是也還是有公塊木匙
Then the round dining table in the middle
然後中間的那個圓形餐桌
They just kind of have that area kind of like the line between the individual and the group
他們就是有點那個區域有點像是個人跟群體之間的界限
stagnant forces like the conflict between national culture and liberalism
像是國家文化跟自由主義的衝突的停滯力
can speak
可以講說
that thank you very much
那個非常謝謝你
Because I think you're actually continuing my question now, right?
因為我覺得你其實現在延續我的問題對不對
and make a comparison
而且做一個比較
That means again two different cultures
就是說再次兩個不同文化
the different way you make them eat
你讓他們採取的不同的這個吃的方式
Does represent a different one
是否代表了一個不同的一個
Embracing Different Values
對於不同價值的擁抱
can i say that
對不對 我可以這樣說嗎
Then can you put your last question in
那你可不可以把最後你的問題在
Ask me at the end in this context
在這個脈絡下最後追問我
what do you mean
你說意義是什麼
can you say a little more, yes
你可不可以再多說一點 對
which part did you say at the end
你說的最後是哪個部分
Oh that's the question you wanted to ask me
喔 就是你要問我的問題
what to do what will you say in the end
怎麼辦 最後你會怎麼說
i mean can i say that
我是說我可以這樣說嗎
Yes, that is to say, the influence of that trend of thought can be
對 就是說那個思潮的影響是可以
customary when reflected in that influence
反映在那個影響時習慣上的
Uh, I think to a very large extent
呃 我是覺得非常大的程度上
should be visible
應該可以看得到
It's pretty obvious in my story, isn't it?
在我的故事裡非常明顯對不對
as they were discussing
就他們在討論的時候
while discussing on the one hand discussing
在討論的時候一方面在討論
How to protect hygiene from combined disease
怎麼樣來保護衛生不感染結合病
Maybe that aspect is also in the
可能那方面其實也是在
Some people are conscious, some people are not
有的人也有意識 有的人沒有意識中
actually you are discussing
其實你在討論
what value are you embracing
你在擁抱什麼樣的價值
What else is worth maintaining, right?
還有什麼是值得維護的對不對
that's why i think so
那所以我是這樣覺得的
I think there are two parts to your question
那您剛剛的問題我覺得有兩個部分
The first part is to say
第一個部分是說
The Japanese way of eating
日本人的那個用餐方式
It should be the way Japan eats
就應該是日本本來就這樣吃
It was only later in Japan that people ate like this, right?
還是日本後來才這樣吃的對不對
I don't know about this
那這個事其實我不知道
i find it very interesting
我覺得非常的有趣
that's what i just said
對那我剛剛只是講的
I just mentioned one I know better, that is
我剛剛舉的一個我比較知道就是說
Conversely
反過來講
You see we were talking about individualism just now, right?
你看我們剛剛都在講individualism對不對
But the Japanese feel that
可是日本人反而覺得說
the way they used to eat
他們原來吃飯的方法
that everyone eats everyone
就是每個人都吃每個人的
Seems like everyone has a little one when eating
好像每個人有一個小小的一個吃的時候
It lacks a sense of family
這樣就缺乏一個家庭感
So I don't understand what is called modern family
所以沒有不了解這什麼叫modern family
So instead they create a
所以他們反而要創造出一個
That round table on Batatami
那個Batatami上的圓桌
can be put away
可以收起來的
so that you can have a western-style modern family
以至於你可以擁有西方式的modern family
So I just actually answered like this
所以我剛剛其實我這樣回答
you mean to say
你們的意思就是說
In fact, in terms of Western civilization
其實就講西方文明來講
Seems like you're not just an individualism
好像這你不只是一個individualism
right
對不對
There is another one called modern family
還有一個什麼叫modern family
What kind of concept is HongSuiHong?
HongSuiHong是什么样的一个概念
Then there is someone in Japan who embraces that part
那日本反而有一个拥抱那个部分的
in this way of dining
在这个用餐的方式中
then i don't know if i have answered your question now
那我不知道我现在有没有回答您的问题
that
那个
you can ask me again
你可以再追问我一下
yes
是
Okay, thank you
好谢谢
matter of time maybe our last question
时间的关系也许我们最后一个问题
Thank you, teacher
谢谢老师
Then the picture I just came over becomes
那我刚刚在过来的图成
In fact, I also read the teacher's article
其实也有在看老师的那篇文章
The article about today's actor
关于就是今天这个演长的那篇文章
In fact, the teacher mentioned later that
那其实老师后面有提到说
About the relationship between the Kuomintang and the Communist Party after 1949
关于1949年之后国共两党他们之间的
That is to say, because of the historical relationship
就是说因为历史的关系
So it means that the Communist Party is ruling on the earth wall of China
所以就是说共产党居统治在中国这块土壁上
Then they are in public health
那他们在公共卫生上面
In fact, there is a very different way
其实有一个很不一样的一个方式
For example, like what the teacher said just now
例如说像刚才老师你讲说
is that they then become
就是他们之后变成是
The so-called social disease thing
所谓的社会性疾病这件事情
There is one such system that happens
就有场一的这样的制度发生
In fact, I have also seen that they regard the matter of personal hygiene as a
其實我也看到他們對於注重個人衛生這件事情反而是當作
It's just that the teacher didn't write in the article just now
就是老師剛剛文章沒寫到說
become an intellectual
變成是一種知識分子的一種
It can be said that they are arrogant or that they are farmers from outside the cloud
可以講傲慢或者說就是他們自外雲農民
So instead they want to invite these intellectuals to
所以他們反而是要請這些知識分子去
For example, going down the mountain to the countryside
譬如說下山下鄉這樣子
Go to the countryside
上山下鄉
Then say to learn from these farmers
然後說去學習這些農民
Then I also want to ask about another one like this
那我也想問說那再這樣的一個
In the process of changing from individualism to collectivism
從個人主義又轉變到又變集體主義的這個過程當中
How have their public health policies changed?
那他們的公共衛生政策有怎樣的改變
wow you this is a big question
哇你這是很大的問題
This is really a very, very big problem
這個真的是一個非常非常大的問題
sorry
對不起
what should i say
那個我該怎麼說才好
Um
嗯
That is to say, in fact, today I
就是說其實我今天這個
What is emphasized here is that there are some
這個裡面比較強調的是有一些
pertaining to cultural values
跟文化價值有關的
In the example you gave
你舉的那個例子裡面
a big part is to say
一個很大的部分就是說
I see what to say
我看要怎麼講
In fact, what I said was actually about
其實我講的那一段其實是講說
The difference between the Kuomintang and the Communist Party is not only the political system
國共之間的不僅是政治體制不一樣
their different ideas
他們的抱持的不同想法
also reflected in their view
也反映在他們認為
What is an awakened person
什麼叫覺醒的人
what is hygiene worth pursuing
什麼是值得追求的衛生
are also different
也都不一樣
Actually, look at what we just said in the Fa lecture.
那其實你看我們剛剛這個講法中
more or less actually you still
多多少少其實你還是
It is the introduction of a Western concept of hygiene
是西方的一個衛生概念的被引入
right
對不對
Awakened person you should
覺醒的人你就應該
Know to use your personal hygiene cup
要知道要用你的個人衛生杯
right
對不對
Even if you think you want to maintain
那就算是你覺得你想要維護
your original family life
你原來的家庭生活
You must at least cooperate with the male chopsticks and the female pool
你也至少要做到配合公塊母池
In order to inevitably transmit the bacteria to other people
以必然把細菌傳染給其他人
then i just
那我剛剛
You said that the guidance of that article is to say
您說那篇文章的引導就是說
I was quite surprised to see that
我蠻吃驚的看到說
That is to say, the Communist Party members in Yan'an will emphasize that
就是說延安的共產黨員會強調說
you should not pay attention to hygiene
你不應該講究衛生
Because you paid attention to hygiene at that time
因為你那時候講究衛生
you will be out of the crowd
你就會脫離群眾
So this instead means that you have not awakened a transition point
所以這反而表示你沒有覺醒的一個轉類點
That's actually what you just asked
那其實我 您剛剛問的
I find it hard to answer
我覺得難以回答的一個地方
It's just that I think this involves a very big problem
就是我覺得這涉及到一個非常大的問題
That is to say, I think the Communist Party and the Kuomintang
就是說我覺得共產黨跟國民黨
there is a very big difference
有一個非常大的不同
Which means they also think they embrace science
就是說他們也認為他們擁抱科學
but they think they can hug
但他們認為他們可以擁抱
is a different science
是一種不同的科學
Science as opposed to the bourgeois West
不同於資產主義的西方的科學
It's a so-called follower of the public
而是一個跟 所謂的跟民眾
A science of mass union
群眾結合的一個科學
And this can become a very different science
而這可以變成一種很不同的科學
Including their later policy on TCM as well
包含他們後來對中醫的政策也是如此
so because you just said
所以因為你剛剛講說
What are the different public health policies
有什麼樣不同的公共衛生政策
In fact, a big one is to say
其實很大一個就是說
They believe they can develop a
他們相信他們可以發展出一個
Used by more people
為更多群眾所使用
To include the policy of TCM
來包含中醫的政策
That's actually a very big subject.
那其實是一個非常大的主題了
that one and another
那那個 而且另外一個
one part is to say
一個部分就是說
Conversely, that is
反過來講就是說
that for example like
那個 譬如說像
Originally, during the period of the Nationalist Party
本來國民黨時期那個
Injection of smallpox vaccine
天花的疫苗的注射
Only a few million people at most
最多只有幾百萬人
1950 to 1950
1950到1950
The CCP has vaccinated 100 to 200 million people
中共就替一兩億人注射了疫苗
So in fact that becomes saying
所以其實那個就變成說
you have an unprecedented strength
你有一個史無前例的力量
to get vaccinated
來注射疫苗
At the same time, it may be behind
同時可能背後就是
The issue of account control
戶口的控制力的問題
That's what we see today
那這也是我們今天看到的就是說
combine
結合
This should belong to Mr. Zeng
這應該是曾老師的
The question of the relationship between the political society is that
政治學會關係那問題就是說
how do you put technology right
你怎麼把科技對不對
one combined with political control
跟政治控制力結合的一個
a story
一個故事
So when you just said
所以您剛剛講的時候
i have a hard time answering
我有點難以回答
I think it's a
我覺得這是個
very large and important
非常大而且很重要的
Important issues
重要的問題
right
對
as we end today's
在我們結束今天的
prior to this knowledge
這個知識相應之前
allow me 30 seconds
容許我30秒
a little advance notice
稍微預告一下
our next speech
我們下一場的演講
when is our next speech
我們下一場演講的時間
it was on april 26
是在4月26號
same time
同一個時間
7:00 to 8:30
7點到8點半
the same place
同一個地點
then we are
那我們這個是
In memory of former Dean Gu
紀念前師量顧院長
Then we invited
那我們邀請到的是
Taipei Medical University
臺北醫學大學
Chair Professor Academician Liu Fang
講座教授劉芳院士
he came to speak for us
他來為我們講
From housing to longevity
從房來到長壽
unlock
解鎖
common mechanism
共同機制
Then if this is because of this series of this in our middle school
那如果這個因為我們中院的這一系列的這個
Dean Gu's
顧院長的
This is a test of fact
這是想驗事實上
Everyone took the initiative to accept and saw that there are really good ones.
大家主動接受看到確實都有很好的這個
The level we have invited are all very outstanding and excellent scholars
水平我們請到都是現在非常傑出優秀的學者
So you are welcome to continue to participate
所以歡迎大家可以繼續參加
So in the end, shall we give the warmest applause
那麼最後我們是不是就以最熱烈的掌聲
Thank you again for our speakers today
再次謝謝我們今天的講者
very good very wonderful speech
非常棒的非常精彩的演講
Thank you, Mr. Lei, Director Lei.
謝謝我們雷老師雷所長
Thank you also to the family of President Wang Gu
也謝謝這個王顧院長的家屬
Ms. Zhang
張女士
Of course, thank you very much for your participation.
那當然特別謝謝在場各位這個來賓的參與
Thank you all, that concludes our lecture today.
謝謝大家我們今天的講座就到這裡結束
Thank you for your participation
謝謝大家的參與
thank you all
謝謝大家
Thank you for your participation today
謝謝各位來賓今天的參與
The first implementation don't forget to take our student belongings
第一項實行別忘記帶走我們的學生物品
so interesting
這麼有趣
Gathering at school
在學校文聚